<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>The faithfull pastor his sad lamentation over, heart-rending challenge and dreadfull thunders against, sharp reproof of, and seasonnable warning to his apostat-flock. In a letter written by a French minister to those over whom the Holy Ghost had made him an overseer upon their wofull defection, renouncing the faith, and joyning in idolatrous worship. Now carefully translated. Together with a word to mourners in Zion who by grace have kept the faith, to sleepers under the storm, and to the almost Christian</title>
            <title>Sad lamentation over, heart-rending challenge and dreadfull thunders against, sharp reproof of, and seasonnable warning to his apostat-flock.</title>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1687</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 199 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 30 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2013-12">2013-12 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A40772</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing F279</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R216409</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99828140</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99828140</idno>
            <idno type="VID">32567</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A40772)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 32567)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 1947:1)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>The faithfull pastor his sad lamentation over, heart-rending challenge and dreadfull thunders against, sharp reproof of, and seasonnable warning to his apostat-flock. In a letter written by a French minister to those over whom the Holy Ghost had made him an overseer upon their wofull defection, renouncing the faith, and joyning in idolatrous worship. Now carefully translated. Together with a word to mourners in Zion who by grace have kept the faith, to sleepers under the storm, and to the almost Christian</title>
                  <title>Sad lamentation over, heart-rending challenge and dreadfull thunders against, sharp reproof of, and seasonnable warning to his apostat-flock.</title>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>56 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>s.n.],</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>[London? :</pubPlace>
                  <date>Printed in the year. 1687.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Place of publication conjectured by Wing.</note>
                  <note>Running title in first part reads: "The faithfull pastors lamentation &amp; warning"; running title in second part reads: "A word to mourners in Zion, and to the secure".</note>
                  <note>"A word to mourners in Zion, to sleepers under the storm, and to the almost Christian" has caption title.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the British Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Christianity --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2012-08</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-08</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-10</date>
            <label>Ali Jakobson</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-10</date>
            <label>Ali Jakobson</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-02</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:32567:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>THE FAITHFULL PASTOR HIS SAD LAMENTATION Over, heart-renting challenge and dreadfull thunders againſt, Sharp reproof of, and ſeaſonnable warning to his APOSTAT-FLOCK.</p>
            <p>In a letter writen by a French Miniſter to thoſe over whom the Holy Ghoſt had made him an overſeer upon their wofull defection, renouncing the faith, and joyning in Idolatrous worship.</p>
            <p>Now carefully tranſlated.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Together with</hi> A word to Mourners in Zion who by Grace have kept the faith, to ſleepers under the ſtorm, and to the almoſt Chriſtian.</p>
            <q>It is a fearfull thing to fall into the hands of the Living God. <bibl>
                  <hi>Heb. 10: V. 31.</hi>
               </bibl>
            </q>
            <q>If any man draw back my Soul chall have no pleaſure in him. <bibl>
                  <hi>Ver. 38.</hi>
               </bibl>
            </q>
            <q>Let him that thinketh he ſtandeth take heed leſt he fall. <bibl>
                  <hi>1 Cor. 10: V. 12.</hi>
               </bibl>
            </q>
            <q>VVill ye alſo go away? <bibl>
                  <hi>John 6: v. 67.</hi>
               </bibl>
            </q>
            <q>To him that overcometh will I grant to ſit with me in my thron. <bibl>
                  <hi>Rev. 3: V. 21.</hi>
               </bibl>
            </q>
            <p>Printed in the Year. 1687.</p>
            <pb facs="tcp:32567:2" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:32567:2" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
               <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
            </gap>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="text">
            <pb facs="tcp:32567:3"/>
            <pb n="3" facs="tcp:32567:3"/>
            <head>THE FAITHFULL PASTOR HIS LAMENTATION, And warning to his APOSTAT-FLOCK.</head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">I</seg> Suppoſe you will be ſurpriſed, after the reading of the firſt lines of this Letter, not to find therein, a preamble ſtuffed with thoſe conſolations you conceive you ſtand in need of in the ſad condition you feell your Conſciences reduced into. I confeſſe, I could wish I were able to accommodate, on this occaſion, my duty to your deſires, and to ſpeak to you at preſent of the things that concern your peace after the ſame manner that I have ſo often formerly ſpoken. But there is a Change happned in your Condition which obligeth me to ſpeak to you in other Language. I have conſulted for your ſake the holy Oracles of the Prophets and Apoſtles, which (as<note n="*" place="bottom">Baſil. enarr. in Pſal. <hi>1.</hi>
               </note> Baſil ſpeaketh) <hi>are a perfect Treaſure of remedies for all the diſeaſes of the Soul; the vertues whereof alley the greateſt pains, and cure the deepeſt wounds.</hi> But I cannot expreſs with what ſorrow of mind I have obſerved that there is not one of theſe remedies fit for you; and if there be any that may be uſefull to you, they are ſuch as are bitter, ſtrong and violent, they rip up and conſume before they give eaſe.</p>
            <p>In what ever condition I conſider the heart of Man, I find for it Comforts in the Goſpell. I find therein wherewith to rejoice the faithfull in thoſe calamities which ſeperate him from that which he loves moſt tenderly; in the hardships of benishment, in the miſeries of poverty, and in the horror of Darkſome priſons, I find therein Conſolations and remedies againſt death it ſelf, which Diſarmes it of its terrours, in what ſoever shape it be repreſented, even tho, beſides its na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turall Dreadfullneſs, it were armed with all the inſtruments of cruelty. But to go farther, I therein find remedies for the wounds of conſcience, and a ſaveing Balm that eaſily cloſeth up the wounds of a broken heart. But this Balm and the reme<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dies are for a certain forth of ſinners, whoſe ſins are not the effects of a ſetled de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liberation; who are loaded and wearyed; who not contented to groan under the burden, uſe ſincere endeavours to be diſcharged of it; who ſo torment and punish themſelves with ſorrow for their ſins, that they ſhow all the ſignes o<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> an ardent deſire to amend them. In a word, they flame with a holy impatience to be delivred out of the dreadfull ſtate of enmity againſt God what ever it coſt them.</p>
            <pb n="4" facs="tcp:32567:4"/>
            <p>But notwithſtanding all the diligence I have uſed in ſearching for Conſolation for a people that have broke their covenant with Jeſus Chriſt, and have preferred by ſolemn Acts, ſubſcriptions and Oaths the profeſſion of a lye to the Truth, the ſervice of the creature, and of idols to the ſervice of the Living God; who con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinue in their ſin without any ſign of repentance; as if they intended by time and cuſtome to render it more familiar and eaſy to their conſcience I ſay notwithſtan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding all my ſearch for comfort to ſuch a people in the word of God, I finde none.</p>
            <p>It is true, the Scriptures ſpeak of ſins of this nature: but every where it is with Sharp challenges, terrible threatnings and thundering declarations of the wrath of God againſt ſuch ſinners. It is not Moſes and the Prophets alone that ſpeak in this manner, Jeſus Chriſt and the Apoſtles do the ſame: the whole Goſpell is full of lively expreſſions of the wrath of God againſt thoſe that perſevere not in the truth.<note n="(a)" place="bottom">Matt. <hi>10.</hi> Marc. <hi>8.</hi> Luke <hi>9.</hi>
               </note> If any man be ashamed of me and deny me before men, him will I deny before my Father and before his holy Angels. He threatens in another place<note n="(b)" place="bottom">Apoc. <hi>3.</hi>
               </note> to ſpue the Luke warme out of his mouth: and the Holy Ghoſt ranks the fearfull among the moſt Deteſtable of all men,<note n="(c)" place="bottom">Apoc. <hi>21.</hi>
               </note> whoſe part shall be in the Lake that burneth with fire and brimſtone. The Apoſtles ſpeak with great vehemency againſt Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>volters,<note n="(d)" place="bottom">2 <hi>Pet.</hi> 2 <hi>Heb.</hi> 10.</note> The laſt condition of theſe men (ſay they) shall be worſe than the firſt. I tremble when I read that which the Apoſtle in the Ep. to the Hebrews de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nounces againſt thoſe<note n="(e)" place="bottom">Ibid. <hi>6.</hi> &amp; <hi>10.</hi>
               </note> who ſin withfully, after that they have received the knowledge of the truth; whom he accuſeth of crucifying the Lord afresh, of renewing of his reproaches, and of trampling under foot the ſon of God; to have counted the blood of the Covenant wherewith they were ſanctified, an unholy thing, and to have done deſpite unto the Spirit of Grace.</p>
            <p>Tho I dar not be ſo ſevere as to affirme that this Doctrine doth preciſely con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cern you. Yet whatever I deſire or hope in this matter, there is reſemblance enough between you and thoſe the Holy Ghoſt ſpeaks of in the foregoing paſſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ges, to make me fear your condition, and to endeavour to draw you, if I can, from ſo dangerous a precipice, ſo neerly bordering on death. What shal I do that I may not labour in vain; I have to do with the diſeaſed that have an averſion to painfull remedies, yet I have no other to give them. I do not find that God hath charged me in his word to flatter the Rebellious, or that he makes me a Diſpen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſer of his conſolations to thoſe who abandon him. Shall I therefore be ſilent be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe I have nothing to ſay that is ſmooth &amp; pleaſant,<note n="(f)" place="bottom">Jer. <hi>6.</hi>
               </note> or shall I ſlightly heal the cruell wound of the daughter of my peopele? Shall I forſake as Jonas a Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſſion to denounce the judgments of God to a ſinfull multitude, or shall I wait with Jeremie,<note n="(g)" place="bottom">Jer. <hi>20.</hi>
               </note> till God conſtrain me to ſpeak<note n="(h)" place="bottom">Eſai. <hi>58.</hi>
               </note> shall I cry aloud? Shall I lift up my voyce as a trumpet to declare to Iſrael his ſin, and to the houſe of Jacob his iniquity? Or shall I act the Counter part? Shall I forſake the flock which Chriſt has given me the Care of, becauſe they have forſaken him? When I ſee the Sheep which he hath redeemed, to wander and go aſtray From the Shepherd and Bishop of their Souls, shall not I run after them, and whatever the danger be,
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:32567:4"/>bring them back to the fold? Dare I not open my mouth to engage this people to acknouledg their ſin, becauſe frighted and Luke-warm as they are, they durſt not open theirs to confeſſe the name of their God?</p>
            <p>No, I cannot reſiſt the ſecret orders of God, who makes me ſenſible that I muſt give an account of your ſouls, if I neglect the means of your converſion; whoſe will it is, at leaſt that I forewarn you of the evils that threaten you, and his wrath againſt you, that I may not be guilty of contributing to your ruine by my ſilence. I will not here follow the maximes of falſe Prophets, who ſay peace when there is no peace; I ſpeak to awake your ſouls out of a mortall ſleep and to alarme you into ſuch a ſorrow and remorſe as may lead you to repentance; not to palliate your ſins or to ſooth your dangerous ſecurity. It is with regrate, that, after having carried ſo long among you the Paſtorall Staff, I should now be for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ced to uſe the more ſevere Rod of Diſcipline. It grieves me that the ſame mouth and pen that has Laboured ſo many years to explaine to you the Myſteries of the Covenant of God, and to apply to you the Conſolations of his grace, muſt now brand you with reproaches. But do it I muſt, you have occaſioned it, your diſeaſe being too great for any milder remedy.</p>
            <p>I will then ſpeak to you, O ſervants of God, formerly faithfull, but now revolted Criminalls: I wil ſpeak in the bitterneſs of my ſoul, O Stragling sheep, and almoſt loſt. Being ſtraitly bound and inforced by the bond of Charity, and by the voice of the call of God, which I feel reſounding in the ſecret receſs of my heart, as from God, and as in the preſence of God, I will ſpeak as a Miniſter of Truth, I will not aggravate your Crime to overwhelm you, I wish to God it were leſs, that at leaſt, preventing my reproaches by repentance, you might make me asham'd for having paſſed the bounds of my diſcourſe by my Hyper<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>boles, and by unreaſonably upbraiding you; But I fear all I have to ſay will fall much short of what you have done, and that your ſin has gone to a degree that my words cannot reach.</p>
            <p>Do not tell me now before hand that I go to accuſe you in a ſafe harbour of reſt and eaſe, wherein I cannot judge of the miſeries of thoſe who were to undergo as you, the fury of a Cruell Tempeſt; The Condition that I am in, gives me a right to ſpeak with more fredom to you than to any other, The share that I have born in the afflictions of the Church has been great enough to authorize me to upbraid the Cowardize of thoſe who yeelded before the fight, and who were affrayed of the ennemy at the firſt threatning of his approach; I am yet blackned with the thunder that ſtruck me, ſtouned with the ſtroak that overthrew me, ſtill dropping with the Shipwrack that ſtriped me, and languishing with the wound that pierced my heart. It pleaſed God, who doth all things wiſely, that you should have alwayes before you continued and publick proofs of my grief, that you may be the leſs offended with the diſgrace I brand you with; and that I may have a right to addreſſe it to you with greater force.</p>
            <p>It is true, I have received mercies from God, which should make me forget my paſſed afflictions. There is no affliction ſo bitter which ought not to yeeld to the ſweetneſs of his Comforts. I ſpeak by experience, his hand has been ſo
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:32567:5"/>good to me that Jought to publish at all times the wonders of his goodneſs. The reſt that he has reſtored to me, is ſo far from making me ſilent, and from hindring me from making you ashamed of your weakneſs, that it gives me a new ground to accuſe you. My happyneſs and my ſufferings do equally condemn you. What I have ſuffred for the ſake of Chriſt and for yours, doth furnish you with an exam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple of what you ought to do on the ſame account. The goodneſs of God to me may be an example to you of what you ought to have hoped, if you had been faithfull. He had more than one bleſſing to give to his children: his bounty was not exhauſted by what he had done for others: there ſtill remained in his treaſure grace and Comfort for you as well as others. Look then on what ſide of me you pleaſe, either as perſecuted by men, or as abounding in the riches of Gods fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vours to me, on all ſides you will find wherewith to ſupport the juſtice of my re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>proaches. One ſide upbraids you for not having the courage to bear a temptation that an infirme man, as your ſelves, has ſuſtained; the other accuſes you of want of faith in the promiſes of God, who is able to give you a hundred fold for what ye might looſe for his Glory. The one shewed you that it was not impoſſible to reſiſt in a matter of ſalvation the alarme of an affrighted body, and the afflictions of frail nature, ſeeing another has overcome them; the other shews your ſin in diſtruſting the riches of the mercies of God, and the ſecret ſprings of his provi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dence, ſeing one of your brethren has experienced them.</p>
            <p>But after all, I dare ſay without ingratitude to God, that the ſad condition you are in, renders me unſenſible of all the adventages it has pleaſed God to con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fer on me. I cannot taſt the ſweetneſs of eaſe when I thinke on thoſe things that should pierce your ſouls. I do not thinke I have eſcaped the perſecution, when I am not accompanied with any of thoſe to whom I have ſo long preached the Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpell; I do not thinke I am ſaved from the ſtorm, when I ſee not one of my flock with whom I might share in the happineſs of a deliverance. I may juſtly ſay that which a holy Bishop of the firſt ages ſaid to thoſe that had revolted as you have done.<note n="*" place="bottom">Cypr. de Lapſ.</note> 
               <hi>I take no delight in my own health, my ſtrength which yet remaines entire, ſufficeth not to alley my grief: for a faithfull Miniſter is more pierced with the wounds of his flock then with his own. The affection I have for your ſalvation works in me the ſame thing that the temptation has done in you, and when I conſider the perſecution wherein you have fallen, compasſion has reduced me to the ſame ſtate as if I had fallen myſelf.</hi> Receive then what I have to ſay to you, either as from a Miniſter, whoſe faithfull ſervices have acquired to him the freedom of ſpeaking what he thinks; or as from one, whoſe tryalls are not unknown to you; or laſtly, as from a friend whoſe compaſſion has in ſome manner involved him in your ſufferings. Be not ſurpriſed if jou find ſome ſmartneſs in my Diſcourſe, as if it were not agreable to the tenderneſs I profeſs; True Charity is never fawning, thô it comply for the benefit of others as there is occaſion. It allwayes intends well, but changes its ſtyle according to different conjunctures. It comforts at one time it cenſures, and threatens at other times.</p>
            <p>What account then can you give me of your apoſtaſie, o people, whom I dare
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:32567:5"/>not call the people of God, ſince you have been ashamed of his name? What in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jury has God done you? wherein has he offended you that you have ſo eaſily re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>volted from his ſervice? What have you found in him to deſerve the indignity you have done him? Have you obſerved any imperfection in his being, or any lye in his Doctrine? In a word, what have you found in his Covenant worthy of your Diſdain? Or what have you found in the new Religion you have embraced, pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ferable to the Religion of Jeſus Chriſt and his Apoſtles? If you have wel compre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hended the infinite difference there is between Idols and the living of God, how could you have revolted from him, to throw your ſelves into the party of Idol-worshippers?</p>
            <p>But perhaps you have not made ſo great an improvement in the Goſpell of Chriſt as to underſtand all the depth of its myſteries, but tho for the time you have been inſtructed, you might have attained to perfection, yet you continue in the ſtate of Infancy: Never the leſs, you have at leaſt Learn'd the firſt principles of Chriſt; and that is enough to render you inexcuſable, and ſtop your mouth in the preſence of God when he shall reveal the ſecrets of our hearts and bring to light the hidden things of darkneſs: You knew enough then when you ſinned, as to forſee the greatneſs of your fall.</p>
            <p>You have Learned that God will be worshipped in Spirit and in truth; that he gives not his Glory to another; that the will not hold the guilty innocent; that Idolatry is an open declaration of warr againſt him; and that in the Scripture-phraſe, its idolatry to hate God: as alſo, that to honour images with veneration, and to fall down before them, is to hate him. What is it then that hath engaged you in an intereſt, ſo contrary to his holy Will, as to embrace a profane, ſuper<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtitious, and idolatrous worship, where the Creature is ſet up in ye place of God, where human traditions make void the Commandments of God; where it is not God who doth reign over the heart, but man that tyrannizeth over the Conſcience.</p>
            <p>You have learned that God is great, holy, powerfull, and glorious; Cloa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thed with light and Majeſty, why then have you entred into a communion where he is other wayes repreſented to you? Where they adore a God of their own making, whom they carry, and shut up in a Box whom they break in pieces and eat? Have you ſo learned Chriſt in the Goſpell, is this the truth according to Godlineſs, which he has revealed? You have promiſed to worship God, which you cannot do, till the ſeed grow up which you have ſown in your fields, a God which cannot be without the Prieſt, and whom the Prieſt cannot make untill the Baker has prepared the matter for him; a God that owes his Divinity to the intention and word of a man, who cannot be God untill it pleaſe the Prieſt to make him ſo, as Tertullian ſaid of the Heathen Gods, whom they conſecrated by Humane authority: Laſtly, a God that can preſerve his Divinity no longer than the conſecrated matter laſteth.</p>
            <p>Speak your Conſcience; Have you thus Learned Chriſt? Has this Myſtery any thing in common with the miſtery of Godlineſs? Has the Doctrine of the Goſpell taught you that you are redeemed by a Saviour which the Prieſt can make
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:32567:6"/>and unmake at his pleaſure? How oft have you heard with indignation the words of the Iſraelites who cryed out in honor of the golden Calf, Behold thy God who brought thee out of the Land of Egypt? And therefore how oft have you con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>demned your ſin before you committed it? There is no difference between you and the blinded Iſraelites, You have promiſed to take for your Saviour the Bread which the Prieſt pretends to tranſubſtantiate, And tho you cry not, Behold thy God, as often as you ſee it in the ſtreets or in the Churches, the worship at leaſt that you have promiſed to give it, is what belongs only to the true Saviour; all the ſteps you are obliged to make, all the acts of your publick profeſſion, cry louder then the Iſraelites, that you acknowledge this new made God for him who ſaved you out of the Spiritual Egypt.</p>
            <p>You have learnt in the Goſpell the nature and excellency of the Sacrifice of Chriſt,<note n="(a)" place="bottom">Hebr. <hi>10.</hi>
               </note> who by one only oblation has perfected for ever thoſe that are ſancti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fied, the infinite price whereof<note n="(b)" place="bottom">Heb. <hi>9.</hi>
               </note> has parchaſed for you an eternal Redemption.</p>
            <p>You have learned that God ſuffers not any Rivall of his Glory, nor our ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viour any in the work of our ſalvation; How then could you ſwear to make ſaints &amp; Angels Sharers of your Religion? I know not how you underſtand it, but I am ſure, if you invocate the Creatures you muſt neceſſarily acknowledg them either for Gods of an inferior Order, to whom you have promiſed to give a proportio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nable adoration; or for Interceſſors, by whom you hope to attaine of God the ſucceſs of your prayers. Chooſe which of them you pleaſe, the Crime of invoca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting them is the ſame: For either you have promiſed to have more Gods then one, which is to rob the true God of that ſervice you ow him, which is to adore no other but him alone; or you give to Chriſt Companions of Mediation, and of his prieſtly Office, whereof Intercesſion is aneſſentiall part, which is to rob Chriſt of his ſaveing Offices that are incommunicable. The frivolous diſtinctions of the Church of Rome are only good to ignorant and wavering men. But God is not put off with ſuch miſerable Shifts, which may as well juſtifie the moſt abo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>minable worship of the Pagans, as the idolatries of the Religion you have imbraced. God in whoſe ſight the moſt ſecret things are naked and open, will not own a Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligion to be true becauſe its Idolatry is maſqued with ſome frivolous diſtinctions: and theſe abſurd excuſes are not a shield ſtrong enough to bear of his vengeance and Curſe from thoſe who put any part of their truſt and confidence in Creatures.</p>
            <p>Have not you yet learned in the word of God the averſion he has to Images and Idols? How then could you promiſe to ſerve thoſe that are adored in Popish Churches; Could you beleive they are not Idols becauſe the Doctors of that Church affect rather to call them Images, as if the Changing the name of things were to Change their natares? Or thinke you that the hommage payed them in that impure Religion, is not to adore them, becauſe its Guides who are ashamed of their own worship, dare not confeſs that they give them true adoration; But can they deny that they ſalute them, ſerve them, and fall down before them? Is not this preciſely the honor God has forbidden to be given to them, Exod. 20. [Thou shall not fall down before them to ſerve them?]</p>
            <pb n="9" facs="tcp:32567:6"/>
            <p>But that I may not offer a Catalogue of all thoſe things that are contrary to Salvation, and which you have promiſed to comply with, I will ſay nothing of Purgatory invented to the diſparagement of the merits of Chriſt, and to throw mens conſciences into Slavery by its terrors; nor of Indulgences, by the trade whereof they have ſet ſin to ſale, and rated the ineſtimable Grace of remiſſion of ſins: Neither will I ſpeak of Confesſion, which, by the maximes, Doctrines and Canons of the Roman Church, that have poiſoned the Lawfull uſe of it, muſt paſs only for a yoke, whoſe weight overwhelms poor ſouls, and is now made one of the ſtrongeſt ſupports of the Antichriſtian Empire: nor of that immenſe authority which the Pope uſurps over the inheritance of the Lord, who gives him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf the proud title of Chriſts Vicar, and of God on earth; nor of a hundred other things contrary to the fundamentall truths of the Goſpell, and inconſiſtent with the hope of Salvation. I will only ask of you how you could ſubmit yourſelves to ſo many ſuperſtitious, mean, childish and ridiculous obſervances, whereof the Roman Piety is compounded, after ſo many years profesſion of a grave, reverend ſerious and holy worship? How could your mouth (dedicated to God, and ſo often ſanctified by the invocation of his name and by the ſinging of his praiſes) pronounce thoſe words that engaged you to ſo many errors that corrupt your rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſonable ſervice; Your mouth, ſo often ſanctified by the frequent uſe of the Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>craments of our Lord, in a ſtrict conformity to the firſt inſtitution, how could it ſwear to thoſe corrupt and blind myſteries, ſupported by monkish fables and pretended traditions? How could your brow, marked with the ſeal of God, ſuf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fer that Glorious Character to de defaced, to take on it the shamefull mark of diſguiſed Paganiſme? How could you put off the Livrey of Jeſus Chriſt, to take the raggs of Slavery to which polluted Babylon has reduced your Conſciences? And how could your heart comply with the mortall deſign of ſacrificing your ſouls to the Devil, by Sacrilegious ſubſcriptions? Were not your eyes covered with darkneſs when they guided your pen in that unhappy deed? Did not your hands refuſe to obey when they were imployed to ſubſcribe the ſentence of your eternall condemnation? Could you endure to be an ornament, to garnish the Triumph of Idols? to follow the pompe of their proceſſions, that you might renounce God with more ſolemnity, and publish your shame with a witneſs.</p>
            <p>Among all theſe things I confeſſe you have done one thing rightly, That you have promiſed and ſubſcribed that you will no more partake of the cup of the Lord, and that you have contented your ſelves with half of his Sacrament. In this, its true, you have done your ſelves juſtice, and have rightly judged that you were not worthy to drink of the Cup of his blood that was<note n="(a)" place="bottom">As you ſuppoſed; but how, and how far indeed ſee pag. <hi>13.</hi> marg.</note> shed for you, ſeing you had not the courage to shed yours for him. But why do I ſpeak of sheding yours for him, you were not ſo much as expoſed to the danger. You forſaw at a great diſtance this extremity, A shaddow of danger frighted you, and you durſt not give the leaſt refuſall that might preſerve you from the shamefull revolt to which they comanded you.</p>
            <p>But if the ſin of this revolt begreat in it ſelf, I find it yet greater when I conſider
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:32567:7"/>it in its circumſtances. It is not the crime of a few particular men, whoſe weak<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs might have given ſcandall to others; it is the Crime of a whole multitude, who have conſpired againſt their own ſalvation. You have made that appear which was never ſeen in any of the perſecutions of former ages, a whole Church haled away, and not one man reſiſted this Lamentable ſtream. It is true, per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſecutions have made a ſad havock of the Church at all times; for all Chriſtians were not Martyrs or Confeſſors. The age of the Apoſtles that flourished with many great examples of Conſtancy, had its Apoſtats: But never was there a per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſecution ſeen to triumphe over a whole Church. Smyrna ſaw a rash Quint us yeeld<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing to the fear of torments to which he unneceſſarily expoſed himſelf: but it ſaw alſo a great number of Chriſtians ſuffer with great conſtancy after the example of Polycarpe. Some faint hearted Chriſtians were ſeen at Lyons, who looſing cou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rage themſelves, cooled the ardor and Zeal of many others;<note n="(a)" place="bottom">Euſeb. Hiſt. Eccl. E. <hi>4.</hi> c. <hi>15.</hi> Ib. Lib. <hi>5.</hi> c. <hi>1.</hi>
               </note> but at the ſame time the Church there was edified by the martyrdom of a great many others.<note n="(b)" place="bottom">Epiſt. Dionyſ. Alexand. ad Flav. Antioch. apud Euſ. Hiſt. lib. <hi>6.</hi> c. <hi>31.</hi>
               </note> The Church of Alexandria in the Reign of Decius, after the publication of his Edict againſt the Chriſtians, ſaw a great many of her members revolt: but shee ſaw alſo many others more renowned who prevented their enemies by freely offering themſelves to death before they were attached; Some indeed fell throw the fear of looſing their Offices: Some were forced by their parents and friends to offer Incenſe, others proteſted they were never Chriſtians; Some reſiſted to Chains but loſt their courage in priſons; and others having ſurmounted the firſt torments were frighted at the ſight of the inſtruments of a new punishment. But a multi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tude of others ſuffered with great Courage their violences, torments, priſons and death it ſelf; Many mo ſaved themſelves by flight, and not daring to expoſe themſelves to their perſecutors were ſecured from Apoſtaſie by a prudent retreat: At Carthage there was a great number of Chriſtians who abandon'd Chriſt to ſave themſelves, but at the ſame time there were a great many generous Martyrs who ſealed the truth of the Goſpell with their own blood. There were many re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolute Confeſſors,<note n="(c)" place="bottom">Ep. Luci. ad Celer. Item Cypr. Ep. <hi>35.</hi>
               </note> whom nether promiſes nor threats could hinder from a con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtant perſeverance in the Chriſtian profeſſion.<note n="(d)" place="bottom">Cypr. de Lapſ.</note> Some there, with the Miniſter, made a prudent retreat, whoſe reſolution to renounce their goods and Country was to them a Kind of Confeſſion; The ſame thing happned in the reigne of Diocletian: the Conſtancy of many was ſhaken by threats and torments, but thouſands are recorded to have ſuffered martyrdom under this Cruel Prince, and the number of them that perſevered muſt needs be great, ſeing for ten years together their Perſecutors found too many to exerciſe their cruelties upon: and after all this was over, the multitude of Chriſtians that remained was ſo great, that it ſtruck their enemies with amazement and fear.</p>
            <p>Run over the Hiſtory of your Fathers, you will find the ſame thing: Many, its true, were baſe and cowardly, but there were alſo many conſtant and faithfull wittneſſes who loſt their eaſe, their goods and life it ſelf for the Reformation that
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:32567:7"/>you have abandonned. Shew to me in that age any one Town that did not pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>duce ſome example of conſtancy, or any one Church that preſerved none of her members in the perſecution? But not to go further, ſearch into the Hiſtory of your own Town, and families: and ye will find there ſome examples that you ought to imitate: for the moſt part of you do ſtill bear the name, and poſſeſs the goods of thoſe that were then either Martyrs or Confeſſors; you are doubly guilty, to have forſaken the truth that of it ſelf is ſo worthy to be preſerved, and to have ſo ill kept the pledge which your fathers left you, when they had purcha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed it with their valour and blood.</p>
            <p>But perhaps it is too great a trouble to you to conſult former ages, ſearch in your own age, and conſider other Churches in your own Province, if there be an example of Apoſtacy like unto yours. The greateſt part, its true, have fallen away, but there is not any place but ſome one or other has ſtood when the battel was ſharp, and kept conſtant for ſome time, and ſuffered to the utmoſt extremity, before they were vanquiſh'd: The moſt part yeelded not till they came to ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcribe the ſentence of their death; They forced their enemies to exhauſt their la<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſting torments, and Cruel politiques, before they could bear them down. You ſee every where the ſpoiling of their goods, and priſons, with other violences, and above all you ſee a great many penitents who have repared their forced fall by a couragions retreat, who fill forreigne Countries, and aedifie their brethren by a voluntary return to the truth, which they had by conſtraint forſaken.</p>
            <p>Is it poſſible, that there is none but you that have given an example of a revolt without exception? What diſmall conſpiracy of a whole Church againſt the Lord, and againſt his Chriſt? At all times and in all places, during the moſt cruell perſecutions, there have been ſome ſaints, ſome faithfull Chriſtians, who have carried upon their Unſhaken Root the Heavenly Commands, who having been fortified by the doctrine of the Goſpell, were not affrayed, neither of Baniſhment, to which they were condemned, nor of the tortures that were prepared for them; neither of the loſſe of their goods, nor of the moſt frightfull puniſhments: Among you only there is found ſo little love to God, ſo little Zeal for his glory, that you have not ſhown one inſtance of fidelity.</p>
            <p>How will ye behave your ſelves in that day, when it ſhall pleaſe God to reſtore peace to his afflicted Church? To whom will you addreſs for a reconcilement, ſeing you have all revolted? Where is the Church among you, that may receive you into her beſome upon your repentance and ſubmiſſion? Seing you have, as I may ſay, extinguiſhed it by your infidelity, So far, that there is not one living member remaining: Whereas God has reſerved ſome thouſands of true Chriſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ans in the Kingdom where you are, how comes it to paſs that you cannot make one of the number? Is there not one left that has not defiled himſelf with an ido<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>latrous worſhip?</p>
            <p>But I miſtake, there has been ſome examples of Chriſtian Courage among you, its true, but they were ſuch as might load you with shame and Confuſion; Five or ſix women and maids were more Zealous then you, who choſe caves and de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerts, rather than to ſubmit to that ſentence of death which you ſealed to your
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:32567:8"/>own deſtruction.<note n="(a)" place="bottom">Id. Ibid.</note> A holy Bishop of old Boaſted that his Church produced women couragious enough to partake with men in the Victory and Crown of Martyrs; but with you all the Glory was on their ſide; That weak ſex ſurmoun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted the temptations that men were affraid of. We have ſeen women triumph over the vanquished men, who reſiſted the evil example of their brothers, fathers and husbands, and raiſed themſelves on the ruines of the ſtronger ſex: who by their conſtancy reproached the others weakneſs and cowardize, ready to cry out with a famous Martyr of the firſt ages, <hi>Farewell my life, farewell my goods:</hi>
               <note n="(b)" place="bottom">Baſil. Serm.</note> 
               <hi>I love rather to looſe all theſe then be guilty of blaſphemy, and impiety againſt God my creator by one ſingle word.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Go on holy and generous women, and if there be any whoſe conſtancy, time, and the example of their relations, has not shaken, perfect ye that which you have begun; perſevere to the end, and your labour shall not be in vain in the Lord; The Crown of life is prepared for you, he is faithfull who has promiſed. Love, and know no more after the flesh, Know no Father but God, no Husband but Chriſt; Keep for him your ſouls which he has redeemed, And Crown with a Chriſtian death your noble beginnings. Call to mind what a holy woman, ready to die for Chriſt, ſaid to thoſe of her Sex that ran out to gaze on her as a Spectacle,<note n="(c)" place="bottom">Baſil. <hi>16.</hi>
               </note> 
               <hi>Dot not alleadge (ſaid she) to me the frailty of our ſex, thereby to shun the trouble that accompanies the profesſion of Piety; We are made of the ſame matter men are of, and created after the image of God as well as they; He did not only take of the flesh of man to make the Woman; But he has made us bone of his bone, and therefore according to the deſign of God, we ought to have as mush patience, courage, and Conſtancy as they.</hi> Thus when Chriſt was taken by the Jews, the moſt part of them abandoned him in the Garden, others denyed him at the High prieſts houſe, but the women were not affraid of his Croſs, and were ready to accompany him with the ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mage of their faith and love even to the grave; Preſerve the Glory of your ſex, and relent not when there remains but one aſſault more to obtaine a compleat Victory.</p>
            <p>But as for you Husbands, leſs couragions then your wives; Fathers and Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers more fearfull and luke warme then your Daughters: was it not enough to commit ſo great a ſin, without making it greater by revolting conſiderately and adviſedly. Should you have ſubmitted your ſalvation to the arbitration of men? Did you uſe art and cunning that you might with more advantage betray the cauſe of God? and Muſt you agree on terms to deſtroy your ſeves. Some of you would not ſin alone, but choſe rather than to want company; to draw in others by your wicked Counſels. But there was not one found among you, who to reſtraine others from this shamefull action, had the Courage to ſpeak with Joshua to thoſe that were going to betray the truth of God.<note n="(d)" place="bottom">
                  <hi>Joſ.</hi> 24.15.</note> 
               <hi>Chooſe you this day the God that you will ſerve, but as for me and my houſe, we will ſerve the Lord.</hi> So far, alas, were you from ſpeaking thus, that you encouraged one another to the mutuall ruine of your ſouls; and to your bad example added your unmercifull exhorta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions; When you ſaw any one whom the importance of the Change kept unreſol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved,
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:32567:8"/>you determined him by your perverſe Counſels, and adopted the words which under the Law deſerved death without mercy.<note n="(a)" place="bottom">
                  <hi>Deut.</hi> 13.6.</note> 
               <hi>Come let us ſerve other Gods.</hi> Thus by an unparalelled conſpiracy, you quickly turn'd the Vineyard of the Lord into a deſart; and made ſlaves of Superſtition a multitude of people whom Chriſt had ſet free.<note n="(b)" place="bottom">The preacht Goſpel, and all Church priviledges are the fruit of Chriſts Death; and thus the unconverted enjoying theſe may be ſaid to be [ſet free by Chriſt] from pagan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iſime, Idolatrq, ſuperſtition: many thus bought <hi>2</hi> Pet. <hi>2. v. 1.</hi> and redeemed by him, who are not redeemed from ſin, wrath, judgement, whatever they themſelves imagine, or others in charity may judge of them.</note>
            </p>
            <p>What was then the reaſon that induced you to this deplorable Apoſtaſy? Were you ignorant that God marked all your Steps, and would one day bring you to an account? Were you ignorant that he ſent you this ſevere tryall that he might prove you, and know the power of thoſe bonds that engaged you to the profeſſion of his ſervice? Were you ignorant, of the indignity done to his Majeſty in Choo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing other Gods before his face? Or laſtly, were you ignorant of the threatnings he has pronunced againſt thoſe who are ashamed of his Covenant, and prefer in his ſight the Worship of a Lye to that of the Truth. You might in ſome ſort be excuſed<note n="(c)" place="bottom">
                  <hi>John</hi> 9.13.</note> 
               <hi>if you were blind,</hi> as Chriſt ſaid to the Jews of his time, but you are inſtructed and enlightned, and therefore<note n="(d)" place="bottom">Ibid.</note> 
               <hi>your ſin remains</hi> in its ful power and guilt. For you have not ſo ſoon forgot your Conductors, nor their inſtructions ſo frequently repeated, after which you went home contented, perſwaded and convinced of the truths they taught you, triumphing over the Diſorder you oft obſerved the enemies of your faith were put unto. How comes it now to paſs that you have abandoned, all on the ſudden and caſt off the profeſſion of ſo ſtrong and ſo evident truths. Have you obſerved that your teachers concealed to you any part of the Counſell of God? Have you perceived that they wrapt up them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves in Myſteries to Diſguiſe the truth? Can you convince them that they have falſified the word of God? Your Conſciences bear witneſs againſt you in their behalf, and tell you, notwithſtanding the ſilence you impoſe on them, that you have done violence to their dictates; and that to ſuppreſs them, you have abuſed your light and judgement.</p>
            <p>But after all, you were willing to perish, and it had been taken for an in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jury to have ſaved you; but did not the intereſt of your families touch your hearts; tho you had loſt your own? Had you no pity on your Infants born, and to be born, whom you your ſelves, to ſay ſo, ſacrificed to impiety? It is not long ſince I ſaw you overcharged with grief when you thought of looſing them at the ſeventh year of their age. You were alarmed and trembled when you ſaw that inhumane deſign executed on ſome of your children and families; Your groans, &amp; tears, with your ſad and compaſſionate behaviour, did then manifeſt the grief you were poſſeſſed with: ah whence comes the change I now obſerve in you? Ye then feared they would force your children into the Roman Church, but now
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:32567:9"/>you freely carry them there your ſelves. Some would have thought it a rem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nant of Comfort that others had done it for them, but you loved rather to ſacrifice them of your own accord: This is a kind of worship like unto that of Moloch, where the parents themſelves were obliged to throw their children into the burn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing arms of the Idol with their own hands, and not to give the leaſt token of com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>paſſion at their innocent Cryes; They have required of you ſomething like this, and you have done it, having willingly deſtroyed and murdered your own child<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ren, you have ſacrificed together with your ſelves thoſe already born, &amp; have made them looſe the ſanctity the Covenant conferred on them, as being born in the Church of Chriſt, You have robbed them of it before they came to age; wherein without you, they might have preſerved it. But to ſay more, you have loſt before hand thoſe that are not yet born; You have bereaved them of the life of their ſoul, before they enjoyed that of the body, and have been their Parricides before you were their fathers.</p>
            <p>What account will you then give of your proceedings, when he shall require of you theſe infants which he had given you? Dare you Confeſs that you have en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>couraged them by your example and Counſell to diſown him before men; and that you caried them in your armes to lay them down at the feet of idols, when becauſe of their tender age, they could not follow you; or that you devoted them to Idolatry before they came into the world? What will you anſwer to the ſecret reproaches of thoſe little babes who will accuſe you of their miſery? One day will they ſay, we might have been born children of the Covenant of God, in the profeſſion of the truth; more happy than thoſe that are born to Kingdoms and Empires; We might have been born into the hope of the Kingdom of Heaven, if our fathers had not envyed us the honor of this happy birth; We have not wil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lingly engaged our ſelves in a ſinfull communion; If we had once taſted of the Truth, we would never have quitted it for a lye; if we had known the table of the Lord and the Heavenly bread, that is there Diſtributed, we would never have partaken of the table of Idols; Our Fathers have betrayed us, and our de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plorable miſery is the effect of their perfidiouſneſs. What will you then anſwer to them; what Defence will you make to an accuſation ſo well founded?</p>
            <p>I do not believe that five or ſix months profeſſion of Popery has ſo hardned, you, as not to perceive the truth of theſe complaints; What excuſe will you make? Perhaps, that ſome favour was shown you, and that they did not require of you an abjuration of thoſe truths you alwayes beleived; as alſo that you man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>aged the intereſt of your ſalvation ſo far as yow were able, and that under hand you were diſpenſed with in thoſe things your conſciences did moſt ſtick at. But can you ſay this with any colour of truth? Did you ſo little examine the Formu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>laries of Confeſſion they made you read, or the Generall clauſes of ſubmiſſion to the Church of Rome that you ſubſcribed; as not to underſtand that they obliged you to approve all that the Church approves of, and to condemn all that she condemnes? and by conſequence to embrace her errors, and to practice the wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ship authorized by her Councils; as alſo to renounce thoſe truths your are convin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ced of, becauſe her Councils have condemned them. How could you be catcht
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:32567:9"/>in ſuch palpable ſnares, when pretending to diſpenſe with ſome things, the more eaſily to dazle you, they engaged you to the whole by a captious generality?</p>
            <p>Moreover, where learn'd you the uſe of thoſe enſnaring accommodations? Could you, without doing deſpite to God the Father and Protector of Truth, yeeld any thing to its prejudice, or compromiſe its rights under the good faith of its ennemies. Truth ſuffers no shuring, it is indiviſible, and where you conſent to looſe a part, you looſe the whole. It has ſomething in its nature ſo pure, that it is violated when aſſociated with the ſmalleſt errors: The leaſt mixture corrupts it; and a corrupted truth is no longer Truth. The Jealouſie of God ſuffers no more a mixture of another Worship with his own, than to preferr another to it: For it is the propertie of true Religion to be inconſiſtent with any other: There<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore by thinking to ſave a part under the pretence of the generall terms of your engagements, you have abandoned the whole, and after having ſubmitted to ſo many errors, you can no longer glory in the truth that remains: it is too much altered to bear ever afterward the honour of that name.</p>
            <p>But ſuppoſe it were not thus, Did you hope they would let you enjoy the ſmall remains of your old Religion, while you were not thorow Papiſts? They promiſed it, you will ſay, But could you beleive they would keep their word to you? Had not you experience enough of the perfidiouſneſs of your pretended converters, to be aſſured you had nothing to hope for, from their promiſe? How often have they ſince the perſecution began, openly violated all the Laws, Oaths, and agreements that might give you the leaſt occaſion of confidence in them? Are their new promiſes more ſolemn and ſacred than the Edict of Nantes that you have ſeen revoked? Or then the Edict of the Revocation it ſelf, in the laſt Article whereof, they promiſed a forbearance to the reſt of the Proteſtants, on whom the very next day after they ſent dragoons to quarter; if once perfidious, It ſuffices to be ever after ſuſpected: You should have been on your guard againſt the promiſes of your ſeducers, whom ſo many fresh experiences had convinced you, to be uncapable of obſerving them.</p>
            <p>But you will reply, that they have forced you to nothing ſince you ſubſcri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bed. It may be ſo, yet this calm ought to be ſuſpected, it is a trick of the Devil to lull you a ſleep by an appearance of reſt: A too great force had kept you awake, tho it would have made you comply with what they pleaſed, yet it might have rooted a deep and laſting reſentment in the bottom of your hearts, and have made you deteſt in ſecret that which they had wreſted from you by force: But however the Devil cannot long bely himſelf, nor ſuffer long in peace thoſe he intends to deſtroy, tho at preſent a deceitfull peace be more advanta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gious to his deſigns. And what needs he more now, ſeing he has obtain'd of you the abjuration of the truth, if it be not to ſecure you in this condition? He can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not drive you into another that is more mortall. His deſign is to accuſtome you to ſlavery, and to render that worship familiar to you, who at firſt ſo much ab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>horred it. He would manage your Conſcience ſo that the alarms of it may daylie diminish, and the ſentiment of your grief may be little and little abate. He knows well that the Cuſtome of that Communion will in time afford you a rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:32567:10"/>not to come out of it; He knows well enough that repentance is made more difficult by a long contracted habit of doing evil; and expects by this dangerous calm that many of you will arrive at the laſt period of life, before you think of re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>covering your ſelves by repentance.</p>
            <p>Will you ſay, you were ſurprized, and the ſtorm reached you before you could forſee it? Can you ſay ſo in Conſcience? How oft did I advertiſe you of the danger that threatned you, both by word and writting? Did I not publickly and private<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, together &amp; apart, purſue you with Counſells and warnings? I have wea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ried you with importunities and frequent repeatings of the ſame things, which I inculcated in ſeaſon and out of ſeaſon, preſent and abſent, every manner of way I thought capable of moveing you. You received the ſame advices from a hundred other hands, and therefore you cannot ſay, without being convinced of the contrary, that you did not expect it.</p>
            <p>But Conſider further how God hath dealt with you in reſpect of others. You ſaw all the other Provinces of the Kingdom ranſackt with violence before it ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>proached you, &amp; in your own Province, error had conquered all the Towns before it attached you. You ſaw therefore the ſtorm ariſe at a diſtance. You ſaw it advance towards you by remarkable Steps, and break in on your neighbours, before it made the leaſt havock among you: Was not this a timely advice for you to be on your guard, and to prepare you ſelves for the fight, or for a flight? to take up the armes of God whereby you might have reſiſted the evill day; or uſed thoſe prudent precautions whereby you might have shunned that Apoſtaſie into which you are fallen? Was not this as a voice from Heaven to you, to fly from the Storm, and to ſecure your ſelves from the Inundation wherein you ſaw your brethren involved?</p>
            <p>It may be the time was short, and warning coming too late gave you not the leaſure to take your meaſures. But why ſo much ceremony to do your duty? So many delays and precautions in ſtead of briske and couragious reſolutions? This was the firſt ſtep of perfidiouſneſs; But with all you had weeks, months and years to prepare your ſelves, you had all occaſions and conveniences deſire<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>able to have ſecured your ſafety; Nothing was wanting to be faithfull, but the courage of being ſo.</p>
            <p>You will perhaps anſwer me, that you were prepared for it, and had taken good reſolutions, but that you were forced, and that you were bereft of your judgment by the evils you ſuffered, and your patience worn out by your Tor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments. I wish to God it were true, and that your Crime had not all the marks of a voluntary defection: But what hurt received you? Did they ſett up Gib<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bets and breaking wheels in every corner of your ſtreets? Or ſaw you any tyed up that were reſolved to perſevere in their duty? Or if this be too much, were you dragged to priſons, or to dark and noiſome dungerous, where many of your brethren in other parts of the Kingdom were shut up? Were you beate, woun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded, torn in peices, or kept awake many nights and days together as ſo many others were? You might have been pitied if you had fainted under thoſe or ſuch like torments. St. Cyprian (de lapſis) ſays; <hi>Thoſe may only complain of torments
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:32567:10"/>who have loſt their courage by ſuffering under them; and thoſe may uſe the excuſe of pain who were vanquished by it.</hi> But this Kind of Apologie doth no way belong to you who have ſuffered nothing; Did they pillage or demolish your houſes, or quar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter ſouldiers on you whoſe Barbarous inſolencies you were not able to endure; Have they reduced you to poverty by taxes and confiſcations? Diſplay to us your miſeries, make an open shew of your ſufferings: I cannot obſerve any foot ſtep of violence done you either in your perſons or families: Your bodyes are ſound and healthy; You ſuffered no loſs of your goods; You are free men, and your trade and commerce has ſuffered little alteration; What then happened? they threatned you with a few dragoons, and preſently you were ſtruck dead with fear, and all your good reſolutions vaniſhed into ſmoak.</p>
            <p>But is ſimple fear a lawfull excuſe for a crime, which neither tortures them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves (if we conſider the merit of the cauſe) nor the moſt cruell puniſhments can excuſe? According to the diſcipline of the firſt Chriſtians, one's defection from the faith, thô torn in pieces with talions of Iron, and bruiſed on the rack, was eſteemed an abominable erime: The very ſpectators of ſo odious a weakneſs trem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bled, and were affraid leſt the dreadfull lightnings of the vengeance of God ſhould ſurpriſe them. They expected no leſs then Claps of thunder from heaven, or that the earth ſhould open its large abyſs to punniſh a miſcreant Church where but one was found to deny Chriſt; What would they have ſaid or done, if they had ſeen a whole Church yeeld to the firſt attackes of fear, their bodies untouched, and their ſtrength entire. Acknowledge ye therefore the truth, and by a ſincere Confeſſion of the evil you have done, give us ſome ground to hope of your re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pentance: Confeſs you have fallen by a temptation that ought not to have ſhaken you; It ſeems it was of you that a<note n="(a)" place="bottom">Cypr. de Lapſ.</note> Holy Biſhop of the third age ſpake, there is ſo great a conformity between you and thoſe whoſe defection he Laments; You have betrayed your faith all on a ſudden, at the firſt threats of the ennemy; you were not overthrown againſt your wills by the violence of the perſecution, but you overthrew your ſelves by a voluntary defection. Does it not ſeem on your account that he addeth what follows; <hi>They did not wait, when they denied the truth, till they were asked a reaſon of their faith; or till they were apprehended, and conſtrained to burn incenſe to Idols, but were vanquiſhed before the Combat, overthrown before they were encounter'd; they did not ſo much as reſerve the excuſe That violence was offered them; They ran to the Palace (or to the Idol Prieſts) of their own accord, and haſted to deliver themſelves up to death as if it had been a thing they long deſired; and as if they had embraced an occaſon that they had long waited for.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Had the Goſpell preached by Chriſt and his Apoſtles made ſo great a progreſs in the world if it had been received Only by thoſe of your temper? Had truth triumphed over error, whoſe Empire was eſtabliſhed by a long preſcription of ages, and mantained by all the powers on earth, if it had not found more faith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full diſciples then you? Had Chriſt been received in the remoteſt parts of the world by a barbarous and ſavage people and adored by the Kings of the earth, if the firſt guardians of his Truth had ſo ill perſerved it as you have don; He is
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:32567:11"/>not beholding to you that he has any faithfull ſervants yet remaining; There would be none to Confeſſe his name, if thoſe who were threatned by the ennemy, and expoſed to his ſtratagems and power, had not had more courage then you.</p>
            <p>The Authors of the deſolation of our Churches were aſhamed of their own Perſidy and cruelties, and to colour the matter they boaſted of the pretended con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſions they procured; which ſtruck all Europe with amazement for they gave out that they forced no body, that the people obeyed the firſt orders of their own accord, and that they retnrned to the Religion of their anceſtors at the firſt ſum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mons. This is that they publiſh by their hired writters, whoſe pens are ſold to impudence and lying, to diſguiſe publick and notorious deeds: Had they not reaſon thus to write, if all your brethren had been as Cowardlie as you were? Your example confirmes their excuſes and makes an Apology for them. In vaine have ſo many thouſands ſaved themſelves, poor and naked, thorow ſo many difficultes and ſnares; in vaine have they filled all the Eſtates of Europ with their complaints, and the account of their miſeries; your conduct has belyed ſo many thouſand witneſſes; And if it (praiſed be God it cannot) ſuffice not to deſtroy their teſtimony, yet it renders their complaints in ſome manner ſuſpected of being too much aggravated: who can beleive all they ſay, tho many of them carry yet about them the Scars of their ſufferings, when they ſee a conſiderable Church thus overcome, and yeeld without fighting?</p>
            <p>But you may ſtill reply, That you were ſo much conſtrained that it appeared in your Countenance then when you ſigned the Abjuration; You were pale, and trembling as if you had been led to the ſlaughter, and tho you ſpoke not againſt the compliance they required of you, your looks, groans and trouble of mind were a ſilent proteſtation againſt the force they uſed: But theſe excuſes con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vict you, and give the greateſt ground to condemne you. When one has recourſe to the deceit of a frivolous excuſe, it is almoſt as much as if he had committed the erime over again: Can any thing more clearly convict you, that you have ſinned againſt your own Light, then to confeſs that you feit in your Conſciences ſo ſtrong oppoſition, or can you take that for an excuſe, that is the cleareſt indi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cation of your weakneſs? ſhould I draw your Portraiture? that which Dems of Alexandria made of ſome weak ſpirited Chriſtians of his time is as proper as if it had been drawn for you. <hi>Some (ſaid he) were ſeen approaching the Altars pale and trembling, as if they were not come to ſacrifice to idols but to offer themſelves for victimes; and on this account the multitude of ſpectators diſdained them, as thoſe who made it openly appear that they came neither to dy nor to ſacrifice.</hi> Do you not know your<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves by the draught of this Picture? You had neither the courage to retaine the profeſſion of your faith, nor the reſolution to renounce it: neither hot nor cold in an occaſion that required the one or other; neither holy enough to prefer the glory of God above all, nor cold enough to ſhew your indifferency then when you repudiated and put away the holy one. Judge ye of the effects of this Luke<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>warmneſs and of what your pretended converters may think when they ſee you give ſo many publick marks of the baſeſt weakneſs.</p>
            <p>What ſhould we have then done, you will ask mee? What ſide ſhould we
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:32567:11"/>have taken in the extremity we were in? You had two meaſures to take, either to have reſiſted, or to have fled; if you had no courage to ſtand it out. It is not given to all to be proof againſt tortures, and to arrive at the higheſt degree of victory. But a victory may be obtained by a retreat as well as by reſiſting: Even thefirſt ages, tho ſevere in this caſe, eſtemed a prudent retraite to be in ſo me degree a victory. But what ſhall we ſay of thoſe who as you have done, would nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther reſiſt nor fly? What can we beleive of them but that they were reſolved be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore hand to do what they did? <hi>He that ſtayed at home to deny at laſt Ieſus Chriſt,</hi> (<hi>ſaid St. Cyprian</hi>
               <note n="(a)" place="bottom">de Lapſis.</note> 
               <hi>in the like caſe</hi>) <hi>ſtayed of purpoſe to do ſo.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>You will anſwer, God forbid that you ſhould have ſo wicked a thought, We would have fled if we could; All wayes of retraite were ſtopt, and thoſe that retired with pasports may ſpeak at their eaſe what they pleaſe, but for others, the ſoldiers and Country were employed againſt them, and double guards ſet at all places whereby they might eſcape: the priſons are full of thoſe they took either on the Frontiers or in ſeaport towns; and terrible were the puniſhments inflicted on them: every one is not Galy-proof, nor can ſuffer the infection of a noiſome Dungeon, where thoſe wretches dye a thouſand times a day. We muſt have done what we did ſooner or later, a few dayes make no great difference.</p>
            <p>I confeſſe it is a ſad caſe; and if you had been detained in your flight it had ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>de appear at leaſt that you were willing to do your duty; Then you might have alledged ſome ſpecious excuſe for your defence, that you were Conſtrained, and that there was no choice but of the Change of religion, or a priſon; And as in the ancient Church they received with compaſſion the excuſes of thoſe who had ſuffe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red the extreameſt pains for the profeſſion of the truth, who to obtain the peace of the Church uſed more their wounds then their tears, and the marks of the tor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures that tore their bodies, than the voice of mourning, as Cyprian ſaid, ſo likewyſe we would have pitied your Chains and priſons. But what right have you to ſpeak of the Dangers of retreat, who never tryed it? You who never loſt ſight of your houſes, your excuſe reſembles that of the Loiturer, who to have a pretence of his Lazyneſs, ſaid<note n="(b)" place="bottom">Prov. <hi>22.</hi>
               </note> there is a lyon without. You ſeek for a pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tence of yeelding to the enemy, Youſay, the paſſages were ſtopt, and a retraite was accompanied with a thouſand dangers, but why ſtayed you til the paſſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ges were ſtopt? You had time enough to ſave your ſelves when they were all open.</p>
            <p>Believe me, Fear made the danger ſeem greater then it was; You might per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>haps have ſeen all the difficulties levelled before you, if you had attempted to ſur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mount them. More then a hundred and fifty thouſand of your brethren who eſcaped the vigilance of the Guards, ſhew what you might have hoped for, if you had, had the courage to expoſe your bodyes for the ſafety of your ſouls The moſt of them that eſcaped, retired ſince the Revocation of the Edict, after they had beſet all the frontier places with guards of ſouldiers; Men, women, and chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren, alone and in company, disappointed the induſtry and diligence of thoſe hunters of ſouls. God wants not ſtill his inviſible thariots to ſave thoſe that hope
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:32567:12"/>in him. He can yet blind, as he has often done, thoſe who oppoſe themſelves to the retraite of his Children.</p>
            <p>Let as then ſpeak the truth, that we may not diſguiſe the cauſe of your defecti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on; The fear of men and love of the world have made you fall; The dread of men has made you forget the fear of God; You were affraid of the Dragoons, (theſe Miſſionaries of the red Dragon) and the fear of falling into their hands made you forget that it was infinitely more terrible to fall into the hands of the Living God; You remembred not that all the injuries of men can only afflict the body, but that God can caſt ſoul and body into Hell ſire; &amp; therefore he was more to be redoubted then men.</p>
            <p>On the other hand, <hi>your Goods ſtack to your heart,</hi>
               <note n="(a)" place="bottom">Cypr. de Lapſ.</note> 
               <hi>The blinded love of thee good things of this world has deceived you,</hi> and perhaps you were not in a condition to retire, becauſe you were chained by the affection you retained for your periſhing riches: ſo true is it that the heart cannot ſhare the ſervice of two Maſters, and that it is impoſſible at the ſame time to ſerve God and Mammon. How unhappy is he who prefers the ſervice of Mammon to that of God! What miſerable gain is it to gain the whole world and to looſe your own ſoul? This love of your goods in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cludes two things equally criminall; Ingratitude and diſtruſt; Firſt, Ingrati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tude, you received thoſe benefits of the bounty of God, and I do not beleive that in proſtrating your ſelves before that Divinity made with mens hands (which you have promiſed to adore) you dare think that it is to it you are indebted for them. It is God, the living God, not made with mens hands, but by whom men are made, who bounhfully beſtowed them, who preſerved them by his Providence, and encreaſed them by his bleſſing: Has he given them, preſerved them, and encreaſed them that you might love them more than him, and prefer them, as your occaſion ſerves, to his ſervice? Is this to give him the due acknow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledgment of his goodneſs, to chooſe rather to renounce his Covenant then the goods you received of him? Has he been bountiful that you might be perfidious? Can you do him a greater indignity then thus to ſet him at nought for the things that periſh, and to ſhew your ſelves more ſlaves to them than religious guardians of his truth? Conſult all ye Maſters that can informe you of the nature of Ingra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>titude, you will find it the blackeſt and moſt ſhamefull degree thereof to uſe be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nefits to the diſſervice of the Benefactor, and to offend him by his own bounty: This is that you have done to God, you have abuſed his liberality to his diſho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour: If he had given you leſs to looſe, perhaps you would have ſerved him more faithfully; But becauſe he made you live at eaſe, and filled you with his treaſure, you could not reſolve to quit for his ſake that which you held of him.</p>
            <p>Secondly, You have diſcovered a ſhamefull diſtruſt, You were affraid you would never receive again what you had abandoned for his ſake, and forgat the<note n="(b)" place="bottom">Mat. <hi>19.</hi>
               </note> promiſe he made to thoſe who love him above all;<note n="(c)" place="bottom">Mark. <hi>10.</hi> Luk. <hi>18.</hi>
               </note> &amp; to every one that hath forſaken houſes or brethren or ſiſters, or father or mother, or wyfe or children or Lands for his names ſake that they ſhal receive an hundred fold in this world, and in the world to come everlaſting life. What think you? Did you believe
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:32567:12"/>he was not true to his word, or that he wanted power?<note n="(a)" place="bottom">
                  <hi>1</hi> Ep. Ioh. <hi>5.</hi>
               </note> Have you made him a lyar by your misbelieif, or<note n="(b)" place="bottom">Pſal. <hi>77.</hi>
               </note> have you limited him by an injurious duſtruſt? Did you think he was not able enough to remunerat you for that you were to ſacrifice for his glory, or that he was not rich enough to anſwer neceſſities? Did you think that he who had given you ſo much, had drained his treaſure by his beneficence? and if you loſt any thing for his intereſt that he was not able to make you amends? The Hiſtories of Abraham, Jacob, Joſeph, and of Job (who were richer after baniſhment, after affliction, after loſſes) and ſo many examples ancient and modern of the care God takes of thoſe who fear him, were they not powerfull enough to make you underſtand what you were to hope from him if you had con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſed his name and ſuffered for his ſake?</p>
            <p>You thought perhaps that the preſent was more ſure then the time to come; and by a carnall prudence you loved rather to Keep what you had then to renoun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ce them for uncertain hopes. But why do not you uſe that prudence to a better purpoſe, to Keep the pledge of the Heavenly truth that was committed to you? Why dit you not hear Jeſus Chriſt calling to you from heaven, where he ſits at the right hand of the Father;<note n="(c)" place="bottom">Apoc. <hi>3.</hi>
               </note> 
               <hi>Hold faſt that which you have, and let no man ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ke your Crown.</hi> You might then have been aſſured that this precious treaſure had not been taken from you. But for thoſe goods [of which you ſaid,<note n="(d)" place="bottom">Job <hi>31.</hi>
               </note> You are my truſt] who promiſed you that they shall not be taken away? Should you think that God will ſuffer you to enjoy them peaceably, who have don ſuch an injury to him by denying his truth? I should lament your condition if I ſaw you conti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nue without being partakers of the Rod which a good Father ſpares not to the Children he loves.<note n="(e)" place="bottom">Hieron. in Oſe. lib. <hi>4.</hi> c. <hi>4.</hi>
               </note> The wrath of God is then great, when after we have ſinned, God<note n="(f)" place="bottom">Nihil inſelicius co cus, nihtlevenit adverſi. Senec. de Prov.</note> treats us as if we were not worthy of his anger; It is the great<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eſt proof of his ſeverity when he will not lead us to repentance even by Chaſtiſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments.<note n="(g)" place="bottom">Auguſt. in Pſal. <hi>98.</hi>
               </note> As for him to whom God is truely mercifull, not only doth he pardon his ſins that he may not ſuffer for them in the world to come but he afflicts a ſinner that he may not take pleaſure in his ſin. He tells you that he rebukes and corrects thoſe whom he loves: It would be a token of his love if he appeared to you with a rod in his hand; And where could the effects of his vengeance fall more juſtly, then on the cauſe of your ſin, then on thoſe good things you have loved better then him? Thus he may make you know your errour, In departing from him; You have loſt that Good which God would not and no power on earth could ever take from you, and have preferred to it riches that he can take from you when he pleaſes: For the Lord gives them, and the Lord rakes them away. You have them from him, and by him only you can preſerve them.</p>
            <p>Perhaps he forbears the rod, to invite you to repentance by the riches of his patience, long ſuffering, and bounty: but let not this delay deceive you;<note n="(h)" place="bottom">Cypr. de Lapſis.</note> You muſt not thinke you have eſcaped becauſe the punishment is delayed, There
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:32567:13"/>is ſo much the more reaſon to fear the effect of this forbearance, that he ſeems thereby to reſerve the ſinner to more ſevere judgments. You have by you, thoſe whom God wil make uſe of to Chaſtize you; thoſe Prieſts, and Monks, thoſe Officers of the Religion you have embraced will be the procurers and inſtru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments of your ruine; They have a mind to your Eſtates after they have devoured your ſouls: Hitherto they have had no advantage by your profeſſing their errors; Your pretended converſion is not the leaſt aime of their intereſſed politiques: Ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to the genius and maximes of their religion (which breaths nothing but riches and grandour) they will, after they have deprived you of the Heavenly Treaſure, deprive you likerwyſe of your earthly riches. Do not think that your obſequious complyance to their Worship will content them, they never pardon that which they call Hereſie, and when one has once undergone that Character, there is no converſion will reconcile him to their jealous Politiques: Hereſie, they think, is a diſcaſe that is never well cured, and Chiefly thoſe He<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reſies which ſtop up the ſprings of their immenſe riches, or overturn the founda<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions of their tyrannicall authority: The reconcilement of Henry the IV. to the Roman Church was not able to ſecure him from a thouſand conſpiracy's, nor at laſt from death; The Jeſuits firſt ſuggeſted that Wicked Counſell in Charles the IX. tyme, of maſſacring thoſe who turnd Catholicks through fear of death; Do you think they have not ſtill the ſame mind, and the ſame opinions yet; I know not if they have a deſign on your life, (God only knows that) It may be the preſent Conſtitution of the ſtate agreeth not with their violent deſigns; Men arrive not to the higheſt degree of miſchief on a ſudden; Perhaps they are prepa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring greater ſtroaks as may be collected from the experiments of inhumanity which have deſolated ſo many Provinces; It was by degrees they came to the per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fidious revocation of the Edict of Nantes; They paſſed from a ſecret hatred to an open war; from war they came to manifeſt injuſtice; and from injuſtice they came again to ſecret craft; and in the end having renounced all Modeſty, from Craft they came to a publick breach of faith; and from thence to force, pillaging, and dragoons. You may by this Lamentable gradation judge what they are like to do, who have published their deſigns by ſo dreadfull beginnings: You have reaſon to fear they will not ſtop here; on the occaſion of ſuppoſed new crimes the difficulty is only to begin, after the firſt ſtep the progreſs is eaſy, and great way is made in a short time in the rode of iniquity.</p>
            <p>But tho it were not thus, do you thinke thoſe men who gape after confiſcati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons and look on you that are rich with the ſame regrate &amp; envy as we look on Uſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rers, that they will ſuffer you to enjoy your riches? Do not you know the depth of their Moralls and maximes? Muſt you try experiments to be convinced of their inhumane intentions?</p>
            <p>Call to mind what you have read of the expulſion of the Moor's; The time that paſſed from their Baptiſme to <hi>Phtl.</hi> 3. could not cure the jealous and diſtruſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full minds of the Catholique King? They were made believe from time to time that the Moriskos, were ſtill Mahometans in their heart, and that they kept in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>telligence with the ennemiesof the State, and on the pretence of ſuch crimes,
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:32567:13"/>that very often were but Calumnies, they took occaſion to ſpoil, pillage, and banish them, and to ruine them by priſons and punishments; The miſerable remnant of the Jewes who had ſetled in Spain, were uſed after the ſame manner<note n="(a)" place="bottom">Iſidor. Chron.</note> 
               <hi>Siſebut</hi> (whom their own Hiſtorians ſay, had a zeal without knowledge) began to force them to embrace the Goſpell, and<note n="(b)" place="bottom">Concil. Tolet. <hi>4.</hi> tom. conc. <hi>5.</hi> Conc. Tolet. <hi>6.</hi>
               </note> 
               <hi>Siſenand</hi> (who ſome time after, ſucceeded) gave ſome moderation to thoſe unjuſt Laws; but <hi>Swinthil</hi> was yet worſe than <hi>Siſebut,</hi> and conſtrained thoſe miſerable people to be baptized againſt their Conſciences, or to leave the Kingdom: But this ſeverity did not re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>medy their diſtruſt, they were from time to time accuſed to be hypocrites, and counterfeit Chriſtians; and there were new decrees made againſt them under <hi>Recceſainthe,</hi>
               <note n="(c)" place="bottom">Tom. <hi>6.</hi> Concil.</note> in the 8, 9, and 10 Councils of Toledo, and all the ancient Laws that were made to ſuppreſs them were confirmed. But as perſecuting zeal is always jealous and reſtleſs, they never thought themſelves ſecure of thoſe new Converts notwithſtanding all the precautions that they had taken;<note n="(d)" place="bottom">Conc. Tolet. <hi>17.</hi> Tom. <hi>6.</hi> Concil.</note> 
               <hi>Egica</hi> found the beſt expedient was to ſuppreſs them utterly by reducing them to ſlavery: They bereaved them of their Eſtates, &amp; of all the rights both of humane ſociety, &amp; of nature it ſelf, of the education of their Children, with the liberty both of their body and conſcience.<note n="(e)" place="bottom">The Hiſtory of the Waldenſes &amp; Albingenſes ſhow how that theſe honeſt ſoules were from time to time ruined by the cheating treaties, and faire promiſes of popiſh rulers.</note>
            </p>
            <p>Com pare your condition with theirs and you will find it agreable enough in the Circumſtances to make you apprehend the like treatment; You were made Catholicks by the ſame expedients that they were made Chriſtians; there is then the ſame reaſon to miſtruſt your ſincerity, and to take the ſame precautions for you that were taken to ſecure them: And that you may not think that this maxi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>me was peculiar to a certain Age and people, it is worth your conſidering, that from the begining of Chriſtianity the Perſecuters diſtruſted thoſe whom fear of puniſhment had reduced to Paganisme, and treated them ſome times with more ſeverity then thoſe who were more conſtant and faithfull; There is a remarkable inſtance of this in the reign of Marcus Aurelius and Verus; Among the Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtians who were priſoners at Lyons, ſome betrayed the farth to ſave their life and eſtate But they were not better uſed then others, and their Apoſtaſy availed them nothing but rendered the Character of their priſons and puniſhments more ſha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>meful: for whereas they imputed to the Martyrs the crime only of being Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtians, they took occaſion of the Apoſtaſy of thoſe others to indite them as Vil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lains and homicides.<note n="(f)" place="bottom">Euſeb. Hiſt. Eccleſs. lib. <hi>5.</hi> c. <hi>4.</hi>
               </note> This is the account that thoſe ancient Chriſtians gave of them in the Letters which they wrot concerning this perſecution.</p>
            <p>You know likewyſe that this is the Nature of the Inquiſition wherever it reigns; It ſufficeth not to be converted, or to renounce; There are ſome Here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſies,
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:32567:14"/>which according to the principles of this deviliſh Inſtitution never obtain pardon, and upon which the pretended Criminal muſt neceſſarily ſuffer either death or the Confiſcation of his Eſtate, with perpetuall infamy: To fall into this cruell extremity, it is not neceſſary to be convicted, it is enough to be ſuſpected, or to have ſome ſtrong intereſt againſt you. Judge ye how neer this touches you, who have ſeen a more cruell Inquiſition then that of Rome &amp; Spain; who have ſeen the Jeſuits the Promoters, may after a while ſee them the executioners of theſe helliſh Laws: You know that in the Religion that you have forſaken, you beleived many things that are of the number of thoſe which they will never forget.</p>
            <p>What will then become of you if the Providence of God deliver you up to be puniſhed at their pleaſure? How empty will you be; There will be nothing left you in Heaven, or in earth; being deprived of your temporall eſtate by your own Converters, and of God by your ſelves. But this is not all, death followeth, You approach unto this terrible paſſage at a great pace, and How many new ter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rours have you added to it by your ſin? At all times its name affrights you, and you wax pale at the leaſt appearance of its approach; What will you do now, you ſee it inevitable? How will you maſter this dreadfull Paſſage with the burden of your Inconſtancy? With what aſſurance will you appear before the throne of God to anſwer his accuſations? What wil you oppoſe to the eternall flames of his Vengeance? Do you beleive that the Communion of a maimed Sacrament, or the adoration of a God that muſt be carryed to your bed ſide to receive your homa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ge, can ſecure you from this terrible judgement?</p>
            <p>You tremble perhaps at the ſight of thoſe diſmall objects that I have preſented to you, and will tell me you will not delay your repentance to this extremity: God grant you may not; I earneſtly pray that by a return of his great mercies he would touch your hearts with a juſt dread of his judgments: Return wandring flock, return unto God whom you have offended, and recover the Profeſſion of the truth which you baſely rejected, and repaire by a bold confeſſion the abju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ration you made. Make it appear by a Speedy converſion that your fall was rather the effect of fear then of a free and deliberate will and choyce.</p>
            <p>You have often made reflection on St. Peters fall, and perhaps compared your own to his: But do not deceive your ſelves, If there be ſome ſmall agreement there is alſo a great diſagreement; You only reſemble his in the moſt diſgracefull part of it; You promiſed to ſuffer all as he did, but you failed much ſooner then he did, He followed his Maſter to the High prieſts houſe, reſolved to keep his ground, but you went to the Prieſts and Judges fully reſolving to renounce the truth; He fell without deliberation and forethought, your fall was concerted and deliberate; But the greateſt difference is, that his defection laſted not long he quickly recovered, there was but a moment of time between his fall and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pentance, and this was a marke that it was not a wilfull ſin he committed: his ſudden bitter and abounding tears evidenced the ſincerity of his heart: Thus a great ſin is in ſome meaſure excuſed, when as ſoon as it is committed it is lamen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted,
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:32567:14"/>repaired, and expiated (to ſay<note n="*" place="bottom">Sin may be ſaid to be waſhen away and expiated by the teares of contri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion &amp; repentance as [a Means.], Iſa. <hi>1. v. 16.</hi> and by the water of Baptiſme as [a ſigne] and [ſeal], Act. <hi>22. v. 16.</hi> But by way of merit and ſatisfaction only by the blood and paſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion of Chriſt. Rev. <hi>1. v. 5.</hi>
               </note> ſo) with the ſacrifice of a broken heart: Has any ſuch thing happned to you? You have ſinned with the Apoſtle, you have fallen through a prodigious weakneſs, but have you by his example reco<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vered your ſelves? Have you amended your fault as he did? Did you ſee with him the Sun neither ryſe nor go down upon your Sin? Alas! it is five or ſix months that you languiſh in this ſad condition, without giving the leaſt token of Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pentance.</p>
            <p>What and do you yet expect to recover yourſelves? How long will ye put off your converſion that is ſo neceſſary? Who promiſed you that the patience of God would not be wearied out with your delayes; but would attend your leaſure. Come out of Babylon my People too much eſtranged from God! Come out of Babylon that you may draw neer unto him; If you will not do it for fear of her ſins, do it at leaſt for fear of being partakers of her plagues. You have time to eſcape, ſeing vengeance is not yet begun, but you cannot avoid it except you ſeperate from that impure Church on whom the juſtice of God, (who is the Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tector of Truth) is ready to be revealed.</p>
            <p>You know there is a kind of wilfull ſin, after having received the knowledge of the Truth, that is never pardoned; a ſin for which there remains no more ſacrifice, a ſin that leaves no iſſue to ſinners but a fearfull looking for of judgment, and of fire which will conſume without mercy: I will not ſay that yours is of this nature, I think and hope better things of you. I would a wake your Conſciences by juſt fears, but I would not ſound a mortall alarme to you; I would grieve you, but not put you into deſpaire. Happy I, if I could work in you a ſorrow that con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>duceth to your ſalvation, I would then bleſs the ſeverity of my complaints, I would rejoice to have made you ſorrowfull, not becauſe you ſorrowed, but be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe your ſorrow wrought Repentance in you.</p>
            <p>Therefore I will not ſay, that the ſin that you have committed againſt God, is that ſin for which there is no remiſſion; I will only ſay they do not much differ; Nor ſhall I aggravate your Crime tho I ſay there is but one ſtep between you and death; You have ſinned againſt truth after you had handled the word of life, and were enlightned with the knowledge of God; Your ſin is accompanyed with ſuch circumſtances as give ground to beleive you ſinned wilfully, and deliberately, againſt the dictates of your mind, and the motions of your heart: Would you know if there be any ground to hope for pardon? It is eaſily known; there is one Character that diſtinguiſheth the unpardonable ſin from all others; It is impoſſible for thoſe that commit it to recover by repentance: Repent therefor and you may be aſſured your ſin has not yet proceeded to ſo dreadfull a degree; but re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pent quickly: I have already told you that Repentance delayed grows every day more difficult; and if the freſhneſs of your ſin be not enough to ſtrike you with horror and remorſe, you will come to it more uneaſily when ſin is rendred fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miliar
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:32567:15"/>to you by a long continued practice.<note n="(a)" place="bottom">Cypr. Ep. ad Pompon.</note> You muſt carefully with draw your ſhip from dangerous places, leſt it ſplit againſt the ſhelves and rocks: you muſt quickly ſave your goods from burning before the threatning fire reach them; It is impoſſible to be ſecure if you remaine long on the frontiers of danger.</p>
            <p>It had been glorious for you to have continued Stedfaſt, and not to have given to your enemies the joy of vanquiſhing your faith; But every one has not the cou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rage to overcome by heroick actions; it is neceſſary therefore for thoſe that have ſtumbled and fallen in the way to the Heavenly Kingdom, to recover and eſta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bliſh themſelves by repentance. Tho the Crown be properly for thoſe that run the race without falling, yet there remains praiſe and honour to thoſe who riſe by repentance.<note n="(b)" place="bottom">Cypr. Ep. <hi>55.</hi> ad Cornel.</note> The firſt degree of happineſs is, without doubt, not to ſin, but the ſecond is to acknowledge the fault, &amp; amend. And the ſecond doth not ſo much differ from the firſt when the amendment is not delayed. We do not find in other perſecutions that all thoſe who fell, continued in their defection: they very oft recovered before they departed from the preſence of their Judges; The faith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full of Lions gloryed that thoſe whom fear ſtruck down, were raiſed with ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour, and returned to the Combat with renewed courage. [Bibliade,] a woman, who denyed thorow weakneſs, and whom the Devil thought he was already ſure of, regained her courage in the midſt of her Torments, and Confeſſed ſhe was a Chriſtian; &amp; many others guilty of the ſame ſin, were reſtored with her: Thoſe who had already eſcaped death and were reſtored to their life and liberty, by the Orders of the Emperours (who then, as it is now in uſe, recompenſed Cowardize, and puniſhed Conſtancy) who were expoſed in publick to be ab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolved of the reproach of being Chriſtians, thoſe I ſay recovered their firſt zeal, and made open Confeſſion of the name of Chriſt, loving rather to die in the com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>munion of the truth, than to enjoy life and liberty, as the price of their denying it.<note n="(c)" place="bottom">Cypr. Epiſt. ad Cornel.</note> St. Cyprian congratulating Cotnelius Biſhop of Rome for the Conſtancy of his Church, writes thus, <hi>How many fell who were reſtored by a glorious Confes<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion, and who became more bold and valiant in the battle, even by the anguiſh of repen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tance.</hi> It was without doubt a great joy to that faithfull Biſhop to ſee his Church imitat his zeal, who was ſo far from ſeeing it diminiſh'd by the defection of its children, that he ſaw it encreaſed by the publick Converſion of thoſe who had faln in the former perſecution: <hi>What a glorious ſpectacle in the eyes of God, what joy of the Church in the preſence of Chriſt, to ſee her march to the battle offered by the enemy; not ſouldiers ſingly, but a whole army of generous Confeſſors.</hi> You have fallen very ſhort of this example; You among whom not one would ſignalize himſelf by a ſingle diſcovery of Conſtancy, But do not add to the ſingular property of your fall, which has been common to all, another fault more ſhamefully ſingular, by continuing in your defection. It is enough that you could all fall, but it would be a prodigy if in ſo generall a fall none of you ſhould riſe again: Repent then, and let your Converſion be as generall, if poſſible as your ſin.</p>
            <p>You have hitherto had ſome pretence of not awaking from this ſleep of ſin: The ſame affrightment that was the cauſe of your ſin has made you perſevere
<pb n="27" facs="tcp:32567:15"/>in it; the ſame love of your eſtates that perverted you, has detained you in your error; the ſame complyance that made you forget God, has deprived you of the courage of reconciling yourſelves to God, leſt you ſhould offend men; ſince that time you have learnt of none who has laboured to bring you back, or thought of curing the deep wounds that you pierced your ſouls with; you have not been aſhamed of your fall, becauſe there was none who reproached you with it: But the caſe is now altered, I come to awake you with my cryes, and to call you to repentance; Take heed that my Labour be not in vaine, and that you be not offended with my exhortations: David had continued almoſt a year in his ſin with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out perceiving it, when Nathan came to break the Charme that allured his Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcience; this Prophet raiſed his voice that he might ſucceed the more; he uſed both reproaches and threatnings, he diſplayed before him a long train of judg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments and threatnings, but yet he carryed the peace of God under the ſeverity of his words; and David no ſooner had ſaid, <hi>I have ſinned,</hi> then he declared, <hi>Thy ſin is pardoned:</hi> Imitate this ſinner in his repentance, and I will imitate the Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phet for your Conſolation. David was ſtruck down with a word, one word made him ſenſible of the horrid guilt of his crime, which a flattering illuſion had diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guiſed to him: On a ſudden being convicted, he confeſſed his fault, and was aſhamed to have committed it. Acknowledg yee therefore yours, after ſo many words of reproach, after ſo many ſtroakes, and what I have brought to de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcribe it.</p>
            <p>It is true, Nathan does not ſpeak to you, but perhaps, he is greater then Nathan, for the leaſt in the Kingdom of Heaven is greater than the greateſt that is born of a woman: ſuch as I am, I ſpeak to you as if God ſpoke to you by me, By the authority of the holy function which I a long time diſcharged among you, whoſe honor I have preſerved notwithſtanding all the ſtorms that have beaten upon me, I may be bold to ſay that you hear Jeſus Chriſt when you hear me, and that you cannot deſpiſe my exhortation without deſpyſing his word: But if this be not enough, hear Jeſus Chriſt himſelf, He ſtill ſpeaks to you in his Goſpell, he ſpeaks to you from Heaven by thoſe motions he excites in your ſouls: Do not you hear your own hearts ſpeak to you in his name,<note n="(a)" place="bottom">Pſal. <hi>27.</hi>
               </note> 
               <hi>ſeek ye my face?</hi> Have I ſhed my blood, ſays he, to be trampled under foot by a people whom I have<note n="(b)" place="bottom">See pag. <hi>25</hi> marg.</note> redeemed? Have I ſanctified the croſs by my ſufferings that you might be aſhamed to carry it after me? Have I carryed your ſins in my body on the croſs for you to loſe the courage of bearing my reproach and of confeſſing my name? was I humbled and emptied, did I bear your burden, your infirmities and miſeries, for you to refuſe to fulfill for my ſake the reſt of my ſufferings? Return unto me, O ye people whom I have ſo muſh loved, and let me not looſe the fruit of my ſorrows and blood; Come unto me, you whoſe conſciences are wearyed and heavy Loaden. I will yet eaſe you, I will yet give you reſt, and ſafety under the ſhadow of my paſtorall ſtaff, and under the reſuge of my ſold; In the Religion you have embraced there is nothing to ſatiate your hungrey ſoul, but I have yet bread for its refreſhment,
<pb n="28" facs="tcp:32567:16"/>and balm for its cure; The words of others do poiſon and kill, but in me only will you find the words of eternall lyſe.</p>
            <p>Therefore, Obey God who wills not the death of a ſinner. One look of Jeſus Chriſt was enough to raiſe a fallen Apoſtle, and this<note n="(a)" place="bottom">Petrus a Petra nomen habuit.</note> Rock at a look as with a ſtroak of thunder, was beat in peices and melted down into a ſtream of bitter tears; God doth now look down on you from the throne of his glory, and his looks are mixed with indignation for your ſin, and compaſſion on your weak<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs; Does not the power of them break your hearts? Can you not ſhed ſuch aboundance of tears as to deface the memory of your ſin?<note n="(b)" place="bottom">Cler. Rom. ad Cypr. Ep. <hi>31.</hi>
               </note> Send your tears to Heaven as Ambaſſadours of your grief; Plead your Cauſe by Groans drawn from the bottom of your heart; and for the reparation of your Crime, let your ſhame and ſorrow for it thus appear: Let your eyes, be a flood of tears, and your heart by painfull ſighs,<note n="(c)" place="bottom">Vide pag. <hi>21.</hi> marg.</note> expiate your Crime either of<note n="(d)" place="bottom">Vid. Ep. <hi>26.</hi> Confeſſ. ad Cypr.</note> beholding or kiſſing Idols: Strengthen your weak hands and feeble knees, and make your paths ſtraight; Harden not your hearts at the voice of God, which this day reſounds in your ears, after you have been ſo long deprived of the Word of Conſolation.</p>
            <p>Muſt the weak ſex every way ſurmount you; They reſiſted better then you did; and of thoſe of them whorevolted, one has given the firſt example of repen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tance: Imitate her courage, and be bold to do that which awoman did: What a ſhame is it, for a dying woman to have had more courage and zeale then ſtrong and vigorous men? Learn by the inhumanity you ſaw exerciſed on her body what you are to expect; and withdraw in time from thoſe among whom ſuch cruelties are accounted pious meritorious actions.</p>
            <p>Be not Scandalized, becauſe you ſee the Goſpell of Jeſus Chriſt out of faſhion: Think it not ſtrange that Judgment has begun at the houſe of God, and that you ſee the Diſciples of our Lord undergo the firy tryall; the ſervant is not better then the Maſter; You muſt not murmur againſt God becauſe he Leads his Children to Glory by tryalls; ſeing he has conſecrated the Prince of our Salva<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion by afflictions: He does you no wrong to treat you as he treated his only Son; And to remove every thing in the afflictions of the Church that may offend you, look unto Jeſus Chriſt the finiſher of your faith, who ſuffered on the croſs, and deſpyſed ſhame; who has been accompanied with a great cloud of witneſſes, whoſe conſtancy God has propoſed for you to imitate: Is it not certain after all,<note n="(e)" place="bottom">
                  <hi>2</hi> Tim. <hi>2.</hi>
               </note> That if we ſuffer with him, we shall alſo reigne with him? How infinitely doth the recompenſe exceed the Sufferings?<note n="(f)" place="bottom">
                  <hi>2</hi> Cor. <hi>4.</hi>
               </note> 
               <hi>A light affliction, which paſſe<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>h away, works in us a far more exceeding and eternall weight of Glory.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Bring forth therefore fruit worthy of Repentance, that we may judge of your ſincerity by your diligence, till then I cannot ſpeak to you as ye would; nor ought you to expect of me words of conſolation, untill you be fitted to receive them by Repentance.<note n="(g)" place="bottom">Bernard <hi>10.</hi> Serm. in Cant.</note> In vain do you lift up your eyes to behold the Heavenly trea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſures
<pb n="29" facs="tcp:32567:16"/>that are the delight of the ſoul, if you have not firſt received the light of ſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rituall confort by the remiſſion of ſins, which diſturb your ſpirituall peace: Seek therefore for pardon by ſorrow for your ſin,<note n="(a)" place="bottom">Id. lib. medit. c. <hi>4.</hi>
               </note> and be ſo troubled for your paſt ſins, that it may forewarn you for the future: Do not think that the Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pentance you ſtand in need of, conſiſts in a bare ſorrow for your ſins paſt; You are never true penitents till you recover out of the condition which you are in: It is moſt true,<note n="(b)" place="bottom">Id. Ibid.</note> that to continue in the ſin which you Lament, is to mock God, and not to repent. In a word, If you would repent, either confeſs your ſin, and Lament the mortall allyance you have made with errour, or retire from thoſe places where the temptation is ſtronger then you can reſiſt.</p>
            <p>How willingly would I then ſet forth the Comforts which the word of God be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtowes on thoſe who have a broken heart; What pleaſure would I then take to draw refreſhment from the fountain of living waters, to communicate them to your thirſty ſouls? What contentment would I take to diſplay unto you the promiſes of grace, and ſpeak of the praiſes of your courage! How boldly would I ſpeak of the aſſiſtance which he gives to theſe that fight for his cauſe? How would I triumph in deſcribing the prize of your labour, and the delights of eternall reſt, where your light afflictions ſhould happily bring you, I would be tranſported with a holy joy in repreſenting God unto you, Comforting your hearts, curing your wounds, wiping away your tears, ſatiating you with his preſence, and crowning you with his glory. Give then O People, who may yet be, if you will, the people of God; give unto thoſe, who have watch'd for your ſouls, the comfort of beholding with joy and glory your Converſion, in ſtead of the ſhame and ſorrow that we are pierced with by your ſin.</p>
            <p>I would willingly thus finiſh all that I have to ſay to you, which is much more pleaſant to me then reproaches and threatnings, but my duty, and the fear of fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vouring your ſecurity by flattering words oblige me to ſpeak to you in other terms; Think therefor ſeriouſly on your condition; Your ſleep will be mortall unleſs you ſpeedily awake, the care that is taken to invite you to Repentance will ſerve only to render you inexcuſable; They are many witneſſes that God can bring to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gether for your conviction, and ſtop your mouth when you ſhall ſtand before him in judgment, His word ſo often preached among you will witneſſe againſt the hardneſs of your hearts which it could not overcome; Your Churches twice de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moliſhed will witnes againſt you that you deſerved not to enjoy them, ſeing you have kept ſo ill the pledge of the truth, that was there taught you; ſo many Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſors, who have forſaken all for Chriſts ſake, will accuſe you of being unworthie of the name and Livery of Chriſt, for whom you could not have the heart to for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſake your goods; All the means and occaſions you have had of ſaving your ſelves from a perverſe generation, which you have let ſlip, will riſe in judgment againſt you, and convince you of preferring the baſe intereſts of the world to that of your ſalvation: I who now labour to bring you back, muſt one day be obliged to de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clare againſt you, that you would not hear my voice, and that I had no fruit of my
<pb n="30" facs="tcp:32567:17"/>care and Counſells; I ſhall then with regrate, at the footſtool of the Throne of God, diſcharge the function of an accuſer and witneſs, and from a Herald of his grace, I ſhall become a ſollicitor of your deſerved Condemnation.</p>
            <p>Fear therefore theſe dreadfull effects of your hardneſs of heart, and tremble at the terrours of God; Think how terrible it is to fall into his hands; think on the ſhame of being diſown'd by Jeſus Chriſt before his Father, and before his An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gels; not to be Chriſts, not to be known by him, to be deprived for ever of his glory, Can any thing be more amazing and frightfull? Repreſent to your<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves how he will ſeperate the ſheep from the Goats, and think on the ſentence which he will pronounce againſt thoſe who are placed on the left hand of his throne: Your buſineſs will not be then with a Regiment of Dragoons and Cui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>raſſiers, who can only hurt the body for a ſhort time, but with immortall execu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tioners who will torment body and ſoul eternally: The Action will not be then about ſome periſhing goods, but concerning the ineſtimable riches of the King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom of God, the loſs whereof can never be repaired.</p>
            <p>Be aſtoniſhed and tremble at the thought of this judgment; and call carneſtly to Jeſus Chriſt who can deliver you from this body of ſin, and habituall corrup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, and pardon your late grievous tranſgreſſions; You can neither do nor ſuffer too much to eſcape the terrible vengeance of God, and the wrath of the Lamb. In fine, it is infinitely better to be partakers for a few moments of the reproaches of Chriſt, that you may afterwards partake eternally of the joy of your Lord, than to enjoy the pleaſures of ſin for a ſeaſon, and afterwards to fall for ever into the horrors of the ſecond death. I pray, that God would reach unto you the arm of his grace to draw you out of the mortall Condition you are in, and would eſta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bliſh you in the way of Salvation, that you may yet perſevere with Jeſus Chriſt in his Temptations, and in the end may be partakers with him in his Kingdom and Glory. AMEN.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Nam peteſt qui pati timet ejus eſſe qui paſſus eſt. Tertul. de fuga in perſecut.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Non admittit ſtatus fidei allegationem necesſitatis delinquendi, quibus una eſt neceſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſitas non delinquendi. Tertul. de Cor. militis.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Noſtri (ut de viris Taceam) pueri &amp; mulierculae tortores ſuos Taciti vincuns &amp; expromere tllis gemitum nec ignis poteſt. Lactant. Div. Inſtit. lib.</hi> 5. <hi>c.</hi> 13.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Ego non habeo alind Contra Papae regnum robuſtius argumentuns quam quod ſine cruce regnat: [ſed tandem cadet Babylon magna.] Rev.</hi> 18. <hi>vers</hi> 2. <hi>Luth. Tom.</hi> 2. <hi>Pag.</hi> 323.</p>
            <div type="part">
               <pb n="31" facs="tcp:32567:17"/>
               <head>A WORD To MOURNERS IN ZION, To SLEEPERS UNDER THE STORM, And to the almoſt CHRISTIAN: With directions to one and other.</head>
               <p>
                  <hi>
                     <seg rend="decorInit">I</seg>S it nothing to yow all ye that paſſe by? behold and ſee if there be any ſorrow like unto my ſorrow in this day of the Lords fierce anger againſt, and heavy hand upon me?</hi> may the Church now ſay with captive mourning Zion, Lam. 1. v. 12. But whatever thoſe do who have no Intereſt in Zion, if her ſons and daughters have no bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wells of ſympathy they muſt be ſpurious, and but titular Children; yea wo to him who ever he be, who is not touched and grieved for the affliction of Joſeph; Am. 6. v. 1, ſeqq, the evil day he puts far away, is coming like an armed man to fall upon him; and what will he do in that day, to whom will he flee for help? Iſa. 10 v. 13, Rev. 6. v. 15, &amp;c. Such ſhall mourn, and mourn eternally, when the Mourners in Zion ſhal be comforted: yet among thoſe who would be accounted Mourners, there is ſo great a difference that many (O if not the moſt part) deſerve not that name and honor; Ah how many mourners are there <hi>in Zion,</hi> who mourn not <hi>for Zion;</hi> their reputation, place, eſtate, eaſe, liberty being in ſuch hazard, (if they not already abridged or robbed of theſe), they may with them Hoſ. 7 v. 14. mourn, cry, and howl for ſuch things, yet not cry unto the Lord with their heart, and for Zion; yea they may add <hi>faſting</hi> to their mourning and crying, yea ſet and monthly faſting, (the Phariſee ſaſted twice in the week Luk. 18. v. 12.) during all the time of the affliction, and yet (with them Zech. 7. v. 5, 6.) not faſt unto the Lord, and for Zion, but for them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves; <hi>Is it ſuch a faſt as I have choſen ſaith the Lord? a day for a man to afflict his ſoul, and not rather to looſe the bands of wickedneſſe, Iſa.</hi> 5, 8. v. 5, 6. <hi>to rent the heart and not the garments, and to turn to the Lord?</hi> Joel. 2. v. 12, 13. yea there may be a tur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning, and yet not a turning with <hi>all</hi> the heart; a looſing of bands, but not all bands of wickedneſs; the right hand, and the right eye muſt be ſpared and kept, no looſeing of its band: many will part with much, yea with all; but not with, the idol itſelf: a partiall repentance, converſion, turning, cannot elevat a man a bove the ſtate of corrupt nature; and can be no evidence that a man <hi>is delivered
<pb n="32" facs="tcp:32567:18"/>from the power of darkneſs, and tranſlated into the Kingdome of our Dear Lord Jeſus;</hi> if thou be a ſon thou muſt <hi>give God thy heart; Pro.</hi> 23 v. 26. <hi>thou muſt give him thine cum ſelf.</hi> 2, <hi>Cor.</hi> 8. v. 5; <hi>[God muſt have all or nothing, he will not part ſtakes with Satan, nor dwell in that heart that hath reſerved a room for an Idol;] a heart and a heart</hi> is the divine<note n="(a)" place="bottom">Leb Veleb. Hebr. Dipſychos. Graec.</note> Character of an unſound heart; tho our ſanctification will not be perfect till this tabernacle be diſſolved, yet no ſin muſt live and reigne in us, no Zoar (tho thou call it a litle one) muſt be ſpared, 1 Joh. 3. v. 8, 9. Gal. 3. v. 10, &amp;c. What doth your faint and partial ſtriving availe, and your being brought neer the Kingdome of heaven if ye enter not in? as good never a white as not the bet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter: ye come to the free market upon the Goſpel Proclamation, Iſa. 55. v. 1. but ye do not offer freely; Chriſt ſeeks none of your money, or what may do you good; but none of your idols, no luſt muſt be kept back; he ſeeks not for uſe, or what is to be kept, but that which muſt be caſt away, or for which thou muſt be caſt into hell; and yet how many part with Chriſt, and looſe the pearle of price for a trifle; they bide and offer, and ſtand all day, prigging with Chriſt, and come ſhort of the high prize, and of ſalvation for a baſe luſt; almoſt per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fwaded to be Chriſtians, and continue in unbelief, almoſt eſcaped, yet abide in Satans ſnare, almoſt waſhen and not purged from their filthineſs; they have many ſores cured, and the plague of the heart not healed, nor removed, and thus are among thoſe <hi>ſeekers to enter in</hi> (<hi>Luk</hi> 13. v. 24.) <hi>who can not</hi> becauſe they <hi>will not,</hi> they will not go alone and without their idols, and among thoſe <hi>ſeekers of Chriſt</hi> (<hi>Joh.</hi> 7. v. 34. <hi>John.</hi> 8. v. 12.) <hi>who ſhall not find him, cannot come where he is, and who li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving in hope ſhall die in their fins.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>We are called to mourning, but Ah where ſhall we begin? what ſhould moſt affect, and moſt deeply wound our hearts? where can we caſt our eye, on what Church not groaning under ſad perſecution felt, or feared? the precious people in the valleyes of Piedmount, the progeny of theſe famous witneſſes of Chriſt, who in the night of papall darkneſs ſhined as lights, and <hi>when all the world wondred after the beaſt,</hi> followed Chriſt fully, and ſealed their teſtimony with their blood, are now become a prey to the popiſh fury, and are driven from their habitations and poſſeſſions; and ſuch as fell in the hand of their adverſaries, put to ſuffer ſuch hard things as may make their eares tingle who hear; and the famous Church of France renowned for their knowledge, conſtancy, zeal, reſolution, ſufferings, and martyrs lying ſo long in the mouth of the Lion is now as it were devoured by it; ſo that he who got his life for a prey, and to whom a door was opened to flee, did more rejoyce then they who ſeiſed on their forſaken dwellings and goods: time would faile, if we did enter on the particular methods of cruelty followed by their mercileſs perſecutors, that theſe who fell in their hands would have judged many deaths rather to be choſen then the barbarous uſage, and lingring torments they were put to; ſo that many ready to ſeale the truth with their blood did faint, denyed the truth, fuccumbed under the temptation, and defiled their conſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence by an abominable renunciation of the truth, and joyning in idolatrous wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip; whoſe caſe tho matter of ſad Lamantation, yet ſhould not be improven to
<pb n="33" facs="tcp:32567:18"/>the reproach of that Church, or for upbraiding thoſe who have forſaken all for the Goſpel; tho the backſliders ſtand in much need of a word of warning, which is ſo ſeaſonably, and zealouſly tendered in the fore-going Epiſtle.</p>
               <p>But tho the ſtate of the Church be ſo ſad upon the account of grievous ſuffe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rings and temptation, yet we ſhould rather mourn for the tranſgreſſions provo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cations and corruption of ſufferers, then for their ſuffering; that the furnace appeareth not to be for purifying and refining, But as it was with that degenerat people Jer 6. v. 29, 30. ſo it is now, <hi>the bellows are brunt, &amp;c.</hi> If we had once hearkened to the voice of the rod it would ſpeak no more wrath to us; if it had don its work it would quickly be gon, and not quarter for one night: But Ah tho we will not hear what it ſaith, yet the Lord heareth what our frame and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſation muttereth under it; Ah is not this its language, <hi>why ſhouid we be ſmitten any more, we will revolt more and more? Oh that my head were waters, and mine eyes a fountain of teares! that I may weep day and night rather for the ſin and provoca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, then the ſtain and oppreſſion of the people called by thy name.</hi> Ah what would a deliverance from trouble profit us, if we were not redeemed and purged from our iniquity? ſuch a preſervation would be but a reſervation for a ſorer ſtroak, and more heavy judgment: Ah our ſpots look not like the ſpots of Childeren, <hi>the beſt now, (as the Prophet once ſadly</hi>
                  <note n="(a)" place="bottom">
                     <hi>Aſich.</hi> 7. v. 2, 4.</note> 
                  <hi>complained) is as a briar, and the moſt upright ſharper then a thorn hedge; the Good man is periſhed out of the Earth, and there is none upright among men,</hi> no Nathaniels, no Iſraelites indeed in whom there is no guile, no Calebs who follow the Lord fully, no Zachariaſes and Eliſabethes who walk in all the commandments and ordinances of the Lord bleamleſs: ſo that I may from a ſad heart with<note n="(b)" place="bottom">Ibid. Ver. <hi>5.</hi>
                  </note> him fay <hi>truſt not in a friend, put no confidence in a guide,</hi> the righteous man Periſheth and is taken to heaven and we lay it not to heart, our Moſeſes and Samuels, our Noahs Daniels and Jobs are departed and gon; Ah where are theſe grave judicious, ſober, zealous miniſters I have ſeen in the Church? where theſe humble ſerious ſincere Chriſtians? But now on the one hand profanity and open impiety, and on the other pride, animoſity, con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tention, and ſaying <hi>ſtand by thy ſelf for I am holier then thou</hi> hath ſuckt out the po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wer and life of religion, ſo that ſome have no more but (and others not ſo much as) a name that they live.</p>
               <p>What (may you ſay) are theſe the words of one ſo often upbraided for his cha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity? But 1, If I had more of Charity: yet 2, what pretence to charity can theſe plead who ſo apparently walk in the broad way, and carry their ditty in their fore<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>head? who will call theſe clean who are wallowing in the mire and lying in it? but 3. as for others I judge not any as to their ſtate, there is one who knoweth and will judge. 4. in the worſt of times God hath his hidden and choſen ones, his thouſands who have not bowed the knee to any idol whether bodily or ſpirituall; and the moſt ſincere uſually leaſt ſeen, and make litle noiſe with their feet while they are walking to heaven: but of many who have taken on a bigge profeſſion, we may boldly with a zealous Ancient ſay, <hi>vel hoc non eſt Evangelium, vel iſti non ſunt Evangelici,</hi> either this is not the Goſpel that we preach, or theſe have not
<pb n="34" facs="tcp:32567:19"/>embraced it, and<note n="*" place="bottom">Sinunc Adam reſurger<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>t &amp; videret hanc inſaniam omnium ordinum, proſecto credo quod praeſtupore tanquam lapis ſtaret. Luth. in Gen. cap. <hi>3.</hi>
                  </note> are not Chriſtians. If Adam were now riſen again he would (ſaid Luther) ſtand as aſtoniſhed at the madneſs of all ranks of perſons wal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king as if they did not mind eternity. 1. Ye earthly minded ones who have Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligion in your mouth, and the world in your heart; ye Mammon-worſhippers cannot Worſhip God in ſpirit and in truth: Mat. 6. v. 24. Eph. 5. v. 5, 1 Tim. 6. v. 9. 2. Ye proud arrogant ſaucie ſupercilious ones, who have not <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="3 letters">
                     <desc>•••</desc>
                  </gap>rnt of Chriſt tobe meek and lowly in heart: Mat. 11. v. 29. Jam. 4. v. 26. Pſa. 138. v. 6. the factious, turbulent, implacable, cenſorious; uncharitable, the evil ſpea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ker who cannot bridle his tongue, not ſparing the moſt innocent if not of his lure, who is never ſo in his element as when ſowing diſcord among bretheren, and reviling the faithfull have abandoned the divine Character of thoſe who will abide in Gods Tabernacle, and who are precious in his ſight. Jam. 3. v. 14.15, 16, 17. Gal. 5. v. 22. 1 Cor. 13. Pſa. 15. v. 33. Pro. 6. v. 19, 3. Ye Herodians who hear gladly, and doe many things, but your right hand and right ey muſt be ſpared, ſaying Naaman-like <hi>in this Lord pardon thy ſervant,</hi> and thou ſhalt be my maſter; ye who have indented with Chriſt on terms of your own choice, and with a reſerve, and the permiſſion and conſent of your darling and maſter luſt, may ſuppoſe ye have two maſters: but Chriſtian be none of them, ye cannot ſerve God and an idol-luſt, Mat. 6. v. 24; Chriſt muſt have the whole heart or he can have none of it; if Satan get a part he hath all; one lake and chink if not ſtopt will as certainly ſink the veſſel as a thouſand, Jam. 2. v. 10. If I might here inſiſt how many particulars fall under this head? But in a word, how can theſe think to find life in the ſcriptures who will not acknowledge them to be the divine infallible unerring rule of life? who dare preſume to judge the rule by which they muſt be judged, who reject and embrace ſo much of it as ſeemeth good in their eyes: thou art inexcuſable O man, and ſelf condemned who profeſſeſt thou art a Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtian, and wilt hearken to Chriſts voice acknowledging all his commands and wayes to be equall and juſt, and yet darſt caſt ſo many of them behind thy back, and ſet up a new and Antiſcripturall way to heaven, in which thou and thy luſts may walk together: Ah doſt thou profeſs thy ſelf to be one of thoſe who <hi>tremble at Gods word,</hi> and yet art not afraid thus to adde or take from it; and doſt not tremble when thou readeſt the dreadfull curſe Rev. 22. v. 18, 19.? theſe few Bri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiſh wretches who having diſowned the late King his authority, dealt more inge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nououſly, tho moſt balsphemously, in razing out of their Bibles (as I heard ſome ſectaries befor them did) the word <hi>King,</hi> where ever they found it; but before they arrived to that hight of impiety they had fallen into many vile and abominable errors, &amp; at length burnt the whole ſcriptures; now tho ye abhor the thoughts of doing ſuch a wicked thing, yet have ye not too far homologated with them? have ye not rejected and caſt Gods word behind your back, ſo many clear and weighty commands, ſo pithily preſſed? and ſo often inculcated? ye durſt not raze them ont of your Bibles, yet would not ſuffer them to be written in your hearts; may not ye who have thus taken a way from the word of life, fear leſt <hi>God take
<pb n="35" facs="tcp:32567:19"/>away your part out of the book of life?</hi> and tho yo have ſome room (and may be a na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>me) in the church here, yet ſhall find no place in the aſſembly of the firſt born in heaven, ye will be ready with the firſt ſadly to regrate and complain of papall and Cefarian indulgences and diſpenſationes with lawes divine and humane, and yet the pope and Ceſar within your own bowells are cheriſhed in their <hi>diſpenſing</hi> with ſo many expreſſe commands of God, and in <hi>indulging</hi> you to live in thoſe ſins he hath ſo ſeverely forbidden.</p>
               <p>What hopes can there be of ſuch almoſt Chriſtians? what hopes of ignorant and formall profeſſours? and what hopes of hypocriticall zelots, ſelf-ſeeking wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhippers, or ſcandalous ranters, that they will ſtand and ride out the ſtorm, if the winds become more boiſterous? But ſuppoſing they may, (for a naturall conſcience, a name, credit, and reputation may engage to do and ſuffer much) yet what credit gain or advantage to the Goſpell could their ſufferings bring? but Oh what a ſad reproach and diſcredit to the honourable cauſe for which they ſuffer muſt their unholy walk, and converſation be? and what a wofull ſcan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dall and ſtumbling block to thoſe that are without? while as the ſufferings of the upright and ſincere, from time to time have proven ſuch a noble attractive to draw ſuch into Chriſt, and a prevailing inducement to embrace the Goſpell hence the ſaying not more common then certain, <hi>ſanguis martyrum ſemen Eccleſiae,</hi> the blood of the Martyrs the ſeed of the Church: <hi>plures efficimur quoties metimur,</hi> the more as <hi>Tertullian</hi> ſaid, they were thus cut down, they encreaſed and multiplied the more; But Ah will ye thus put Chriſt and his glorious Goſpell to an open ſhame, while ye pretend to ſuffer for him and his cauſe? will ye loſe the honour and reward of your ſufferings by your ungoſpel-like life and de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>portment?</p>
               <p>But O ye in whom are any grains of ſincerity and uprightneſs, in whom is found <hi>the root of the matter,</hi> your ſufferings and blood are precious in the ſight of the Lord: and how are ye engaged to glorifie God as by your ſufferings, ſo by your humility, ſelf deniall, zeal, and holy converſation, and think it not enough to ſuffer for him, unleſs ye profit by your ſufferings, reap the ſweet fruit that groweth on a ſanctified croſs, and improve the rod as your talent for to be laid out for your Maſters honour, unleſs ye hear its voice, and conſider what it ſaith; and unleſs the furnace become refining and purging to you: now ye are called afreſh to try and ſearch your wayes, to labour after a greater meaſure of ſincerity mortification, humility, ſelf-deniall, charity, tenderneſs, zeal, cir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cumſpection: now ye are called to be more frequent and fervent in prayer, to be much in the exerciſe of meditation, faſting, reading the ſriptures, and fearching after directions and conſolations ſutable to your triall; there be many graces ye are now in a ſperiall manner called to exerciſe, and many duties ye are obliged to perform: and O do not ſlight that mercy, that while ſo many having made ſhipwrack of the faith and of a good Conſcience are called to Lament and mourn, and are held on the rack by their feares and horrour, you having by Grace been enabled to ſtand out under ſuch a terrible and laſting triall are called to abound in thankfullneſs, and to rejoyce: the times are ſad, your Loſſes may be great,
<pb n="36" facs="tcp:32567:20"/>and you haye nothing in hand, no proviſion for to morrow and none of your friends or relations at hand, yet how much are ye Concerned to rejoyce, to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>joyce and be exceeding glad, for great is your priviledge, and great ſhall your Reward in heaven be; Phil. 1. v. 29. Mat. 5. v. 22. your ſympathizing Brethe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ren who look on you with ſad hearts yet rejoyce in your ſtedfaſtneſs; ye are your faithfull paſtors joy and Crown, as they Phil. 1. v. 1. Theſſ. 2. v. 19. were Pauls; the bleſſed name of our Lord Jeſus Chriſt hath been glorified in you as in them, 2 Theſſ. 1. v. 12. and may I not ſay of you what is ſaid of theſe 2 Cor. 8. v. 23. O read it, I ſcarce dare ſpeak it and ſay, <hi>ye are the Glory of Chriſt,</hi> but he by his Apoſtle hath ſaid it, and as he hath honoured you to be his faithfull witneſſes to aſſert his truth, and to be precious Inſtruments to hold forth his Glory befor a perſecuting and backſliding generation, ſo he will glorifie you befor Angels and men; and ye who have owned him now ſhall be owned by him when he will ſay unto the fearfull and unbeliever depart from me I know you not.</p>
               <p>O think you ſee Chriſt putting the crown of glory on your heads when ye ſee men pletting a crown of thorns for you: ſay with the martyrs when ſtript na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ked, and ſhut out in the winter night to the open air, to be tormented with the nipping froſt, <hi>the air is ſharp, the cold gresvous, but there is a ſweet repoſe and reſt in Abrahams boſom;</hi> this night will ſhortly over and paſs, your<note n="*" place="bottom">Nubecula eſt cito tranſitura. Athanaſ.</note> ten dayes tribu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lation, and Satans licence (Rev. 2. v. 10.) to impriſon and torment you, will quickly expire, and then a bleſſed, long laſting, everlaſting Eternity of liber<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty, joy, and ſoul ſatisfying, unconceiveable felicity, glory, perfection. Sup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe ye ſee Chriſt now ſtanding with a napkin in his hand to wip all teares from your eyes, Rev. 7. v. 17. and with a pen in his hand writing down, and holding a bottle to receive all your teares; all are booked and botled. Pſal. 59. v. 8. ſuppoſe ye ſee the Angels rejoycing in your valour, and ſtedſaſtneſs; (as they did Luk. 15. v. 10. Yea and more then at thy firſt converſion) and that ye hear the Lord ſtopping the mouth of the accuſer of the bretheren with your faithfullneſs, and conſtancy as weell as once with his, Job 2. v. 3. ſuppoſe ye ſee Chriſt wel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>coming you to heaven, and ſaying to his Father what once the Angel ſaid to John of your Brethren, Rev. 7. v. 14, 15, 16, 17. <hi>theſe are they which came out of great tribulation, and have waſhed their robes, and made them white in my blood, let them come before thy throne &amp;c.</hi> and will he not owne, and make good his precious pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſe Mat. 19. v. 29. Mark. 10. v. 30. and ſay theſe are they who have forſaken houſe Lands, countrey and all that was dear to them, for my name, and Goſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pels-ſake, let them have the great and glorious recompence I have purchaſed for them, and promiſed to them. O then <hi>watch ye</hi> while a ſecure world is faſt a ſleep; <hi>ſtand faſt in the faith, quite you like men, be ſtrong,</hi> 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 10. v. 13. <hi>in noth<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing terrified by your adverſaries, which is to them an evident token of perdition, but to you of ſalvation. and that of God. Phil.</hi> 1. v. 26. and conſider the more ſharp the triall is, the more glory ye bring to Chriſt, his Goſpel, and truth; and let it be on record to the ſucceeding generations, and to your praiſe, that ye did cleave to Chriſt, and abode with him in an hour of ſuch terrible temptation, while
<pb n="37" facs="tcp:32567:20"/>the perſecution was (in ſome reſpect) more hot then the <hi>Neroman, Decian,</hi> or <hi>Diocletian,</hi> and the methods more barbarous, cruel, and ſubtile then any inven<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted for tormenting the primitive Chriſtians by mercileſs pagan Emperours. <hi>Finally my Bretheren be ſtrong in the Lord, and in the power of his might; take unto you the whole armour of God, that ye may be able to withſtand in the evil day, and having done and ſuffered all to ſtand.</hi> Eph. 6. v. 10, 13, &amp;c. the eye of your Captain, (who is the captain of ſalvation) his encouraging eye is on you; and his ſupporting arme under you, and let your eye be towards him, and your hands imployed in fighting valiantly under his banner, in his name, and for his cauſe; O do ye not ſee him with the crown of glory in his hand, and hear him ſaying, ſo fight and ſtrive that ye may obtain, 1 Cor. 9. v. 24, 25. <hi>to him that overcometh will I give to eat of the tree of life, and of the hidden Manna; I will give him a white ſtone, and a new name which no man knoweth but he that receiveth it; I will give him the morning ſtar, cloath him with white raiment, and he ſhaell walk with me in white; I will make him a pillar in the temple of my God, and will confeſs his name before my Father and his Angels; yea (O read and admire) I will grant to him to ſit with me on my throne; And becauſe he hath kept the word of my patience, I will alſo keep him from the hour of temptation which ſhall come upon all the world, to try them.</hi> Rev. 2. v. 7, 17, 28. Rev. 3. v. 4, 5, 10, 12, 21. dare ye then complain? will ye fear or faint; who is he (Devil or man) that can harm you while ye thus follow that which is good? 1 Pet. 3. v. 13. ye muſt prevaile and carry the day, be conquerours, and more then conquerours, yea in all theſe things in which your enemies ſeem to triumph over you; your loſs ſhall be your great gain, your trouble, pain, blood, ſorrow, anguiſh, work out your unſpeakable joy and conſolation, your ſecurity, ſafety and eternall ſalvation; and your reproach for Chriſt ſhall be your crown, and name of praiſe; Rom. 8. v. 37. Rev. 12. v. 11. <hi>wherfor lift up the hands which hang down, and the feeble knees and let your feet ſtill, walk in ſtreight paths:</hi> Heb. 12. v. 12, 13. wherefore is thy countenance ſad, art not thou a Kings ſon? Let not your enemies think ye ſerve a hard maſter, and have an unkind Father; and that ye live by ſenſe, while ye are contending for the faith, but let them know ye have meat they know not of, ye have proviſions, conſolations, and ſupporting in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fluences and ſupplies they are ſtrangers to, and intermedle not with; and ſay to ſuch of them as have any relicks of naturall tenderneſs, weep not for us but for your<note n="*" place="bottom">Vide Lactantium de mortibus perſecutorum.</note> ſelves, and your Children: and do not exclude the moſt mercileſs perſecu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tors from your compaſſion, but pray for them while they are digging pits for you; yet let your compaſſion in a ſpeciall manner be extended to your Apoſtat-Bre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>theren; let your bowells yern upon them; O wreſtle, pray, and cry mightily unto God that he may pity and recover theſe backſliders; Oh how deplorable is their caſe? and how can their hearts endure in the day the Lord ſhall deale with them? or if now they would but conſider theſe dreadfull and awaking Scriptures, Mat. 10. v. 33. Mark. 8. v. 38. Heb. 6. v. 4, 5, 6. Heb. 10. v. 26, 27, 31, 38. If their conſciences be not ſeared as with an hot iron their life muſt be (and we hear to many it is) more bitter to them then many deaths: thus their dreadfull
<pb n="38" facs="tcp:32567:21"/>fall ſhould be ſo far from occaſioning your ſtumbling, and inviting you to follow their ſteps, that it ſhould mightily provoke you to conſtancy, and out of Gra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>titude to him by whoſe Grace ye have been upheld make you (when by their ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ample tempted to renounce the faith) ſay what theſe renowned Martyrs ſaid to their pagan-perſecutors tempting them to ſacrifice to an Idol, becauſe their fellows and Companions had done ſo, and telling them they were not wiſer nor better then they, <hi>nay (ſaid theſe worthies of the Lord and O Let the ſame mind be in you) but we will the rather, ſtand to make up the wofull breach theſe have made; and we are ready to ſacrifice our Lives by your hands to the honour of our God whom they by their Idolatrous ſacrifice have ſo much diſhonoured.</hi> O ye excellent ones and Dearly beloved go on and continue to be with theſe precious ſouls the repairers of the Lamentable breaches made in our Zion by theſe fallen ſtars in this day of viſitation: and then 2, let this provoke you to thankfullneſs and to admire his unſpeakable Love to you, by whoſe ſupporting influences ye have been enabled to ſtand under theſe boiſterous ſtorms and tempeſts; that poor nothing worm ye have been ſtrengthned to ſtand under ſuch violent and ſtrong temptations: O how are ye Concerned to praiſe your holy and omnipotent keeper, counſeller, and guide; and under all your pinching ſtraits and hard meaſures from adverſaries to rejoyce that, <hi>ye are not of them who have drawn back unto perdition:</hi> as for theſe poor ſouls who have put there ſalvation to ſuch a venture, I need not ſpeak to their caſe, (tho it here fall in) that being ſo fully and faithfully conſidered in the foregoing Epiſtle, to which I commend you, as for warning to <hi>take</hi>
                  <note n="(a)" place="bottom">1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 10. v. 12.</note> 
                  <hi>heed that ye fall not,</hi> ſo to excite you to abound more and more in praiſing him <hi>who hitherto hath kept you from fal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling, and is</hi>
                  <note n="(b)" place="bottom">
                     <hi>Iud.</hi> v. 24, 25.</note> 
                  <hi>able to preſent you faultleſs befor the preſence of his Glory with excee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding joy.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>I ſtopt here, reſolving to add no more, but while the preſs was going I began more ſeriouſly to conſider that the time did call, and that as the need ſo the deſire of many might invite to ſtay a while in offering ſome ſeaſonable directions how to carry in ſuch a day, by putting one and other in mind of the moſt concerning duties now to be performed; and in warning of the ſnares, precipices, ſins and offences to be carefully avoided and guarded againſt, for ſtirring up one and other to walk as becometh Chriſtians indeed, and ſuch as are ſenſible of the wrath gone out againſt us: let me then in all humility and tenderneſs offer, and as a Miniſter of Chriſt in his name and authority require you as you will anſwer to him in the day of accounts to hearken to the following durections from his word.</p>
               <p n="1">1. Then I would intreat and obteſt you <hi>to make Religion your Buſineſs,</hi> and not to ſerve God in the by: O be more zealous for Gods Glory, and more carefull about matters of ſoul concernment then for periſhing trifles; asknowing there is but one thing neceſſary. Mat. 6. v. 33. Joh. 6. v. 27. Coloſſ. 3. v. 2. Luk to v. 24. often putting up to your ſouls the queſtion our Bliſſed Lord hath offered to your moſt ſerious conſideration Mat. 16. v. 26. <hi>What is a man profited, if he ſhall gain the whole world and loſe his own ſoul?</hi> if thou ſtep out of the way, thou mayeſt fall among theeves who will rob thee of that jewell; O Remember the way is a nar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>row
<pb n="39" facs="tcp:32567:21"/>way, with difficulty diligence and circumſpection kept and walked in, Mat. 7. v. 31. Phil. 2. v. 12. 2. Pet. 1. v. 5. ſeqq. hence.</p>
               <p n="2">2. Walk circumſpectly, Eph. 5. v. 15. taking heed to all your ſteps watching over your thoughts words and whole deportment, that it may be ſuch as becometh the Goſpell of Chriſt: O how are ye concerned (eſpecially now,) <hi>to make the light of your holy Converſation ſo to ſhine that others ſeing your Good works (and you by theſe) may Glorify your father which is in heaven,</hi> Mat. 5. v. 16. that the<note n="*" place="bottom">Vexatio dat intellectum, Schola crucis Schola Lucis. Cypr. Serm. <hi>4.</hi> de immort.</note> ſaying may hold in you, <hi>the School of affliction is the School of light and inſtruction.</hi> O then take heed ye make not the Goſpell which ye profeſs, and for which, <hi>ye ſuffer,</hi> and are ready (as ye pretend) to ſuffer the loſſe of al things, <hi>ſuffer by you,</hi> and be<note n="†" place="bottom">Blaſphemiam ingerit relegioni quam colit qui quod confitetur, non ante omnes imple<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verit. Cypr. de Sin Clericorum.</note> reproached by your ungoſpel like carriage: your ſteps are narrowly marked; by the ſin of a David, <hi>occaſion was given to the Enemies of the Lord to blaſpheme;</hi> 2 Sam. 12. v. 14. by a blot in thy carriage (tho it were but in reference to thy relative duties) <hi>the name of God and his doctrin may be blasſphemed.</hi> 1 Tim. 6. v. 1; Ah wilt thou diſho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour, and wrong the honourable cauſe for which thou ſuffereſt, by thy ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gligent walk and unſutable converſation? <hi>O look to your ſelves that ye loſe not thoſe things ye have wrought, but receive the great reward.</hi> 2. Ioh. 8. there may be much done and much ſufferred for a good cauſe, and all amount to nothing. 1 Cor 13. v. 2; 3. O watch over your hearts and wayes! ye are now placed ſentinels, the enemy is ready to break in, and make a prey of all if he find us ſleeping; Satan will be now ready to tempt, knowing what a provocation it is, to ſin in the face of judgements and in a time of wrath and indignation; <hi>Remember Lots wif.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="3">3. Walk prudently, as wiſe not as fools: Eph. 5. v. 15. hearken to Chriſts Counſell, and joyn prudence with your innocency; Mat. 10. v. 16. now ſatan will be ready to ſow his tares, to put on his ſurplice, and transform him ſelf into an Angel of light; &amp; if he Cannot make thee ſplit on the rock of profanity &amp; looſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs, he will ſtrive to ſink thee in the gulf of errour and irregularities. O be In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>treated therfore <hi>not to Believe every ſpirit but try whither it be of God or not</hi> 1 <hi>Joh.</hi> 4. v. 1. <hi>take heed what ye hear and how ye hear.</hi> 1 <hi>Theſſ.</hi> 5. v. 21. <hi>Act.</hi> 17. v. 11. O what a noble ornament is prudence to religion, and how ready are imprudent Zelots to caſt a ſtumbling block in the way of the profane, and to furniſh the triumph of Papiſts by their heady, raſh, irregular actings, and wild fancies? O better you had never been born, then thus to raiſe an evil report on Religion, to caſt a ſtumbling-block in the way of them who are ready to break their necks without your help and to harden thoſe in their evil way who are but too reſolute to go on therein.</p>
               <p n="4">4. Redeem time from the world, its work, buſineſs, fellowſhip; and lay it out for God and for eternity; and ye ſhal be (ye can be) no looſers; for then ye will trade with Chriſt, and for his gold that will make you Rich indeed, you will not run as uncertain, and beat the air, you will not purſue ſhadowes, and
<pb n="40" facs="tcp:32567:22"/>periſh in the purſuit; but will run and obtain, fight and prevaile, and carry the prize and Crown of Glory. Eph. 5. v. 16. Rev. 3. v. 18. 1 Cor. 9. v. 26.</p>
               <p n="5">5. In a time of ſuch perplexity, and uncertainly Labour to ſecure 1. the trea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure and pearle of prize; 2 Pet. 1. v. 10. if it be in ſaftie what need we value the loſs of periſhing trifles? 2. Provide a retiring and reſting place and when you eſpy no city of refuge, run to the ſtrong rock, and provid you Chambers there; and however tempeſtuous the ſtorm may become. ye need not fear. Iſa. 26 v. 20. Pro. 18. v. 10. Pſal. 61. v. 23. 3<hi rend="sup">dly</hi> while there is ſo litle love and kindneſs to be pected from men, and ſo litle truth and fidelyty among them, ſo that we may take up the word. Mic. 7. v. 5.6.4. rejoyce that ye have a friend in heaven, to whom ye may run, and whom ye may ſafely truſt; and when ye find litle com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fort in converſing with men let your Converſation be in heaven; be frequent and ſervent in your udreſſes to God, and carefull to mantain a fellowſhip with the father &amp; his ſon Jeſus Chriſt; be much in prayer, Meditation, reading, &amp; take heed how ye perform theſe duties Phil. 2. v. 20. Joh. 2. v. 3. Luk. 8. v. 18. Heb. 4. v. 2. Jam. 1. v. 2, 22, 23. but you will ſay, what could diſcourage us if theſe were ſecured? But how may that be don? Anſ. as to the firſt an heavenly Converſation is the beſt way to ſecure the heavenly treaſure. Coloſſ. 3. v. 2, 4. As to the ſecond run in to that rock, and theſe Chambers of ſecurity by faith; if thou thus caſt thy ſelf and all thy burdens on the Lord he ſhall ſuſtain and care for thee: Pſal. 55. v. 22. 1 Pet. 5. v. 7; If with him Pſal. 61. v. 4. thou <hi>truſt in the Covert of his wings,</hi> thou mayeſt with him. Pſa. 63. v. 7. <hi>Rejoyce under their ſhadow:</hi> O then, <hi>when thy heart is overwhelmed,</hi> ſay with that eminent Believer Pſa. 61. v. 12. <hi>Hear my cry o God, and lead me to the Rock that is higher then I.</hi> As to the 3<hi rend="sup">d</hi>, our Bleſſed Lord aſſures you that ye are his friends, and ſhal abide in his love if ye keep his Commandments, and do what ſoever he bids you. Joh. 15. v. 10, 14.</p>
               <p n="6">6. Set the Lord allways befor you, and walk as under his all ſeeing eye, and as hearing the ſound of the laſt trumpet in your eares, and ſummoning you to judgement, to give an accompt of all ye have don and ſaid Pſa. 16. v. 9. 2 Cor. 5. v. 5, 10.</p>
               <p n="7">7. Be tender and<note n="*" place="bottom">Audaciam exiſtimo de bono divini precepti diſputare, nec quia bonum eſt (i. e. nobis videtur) auſcultare debemus, ſed quia Deus pracepit. Tertul. de panit.</note> tremble at the word of God, at the whole word, not daring to caſt any part of it behind thy back; O ſaid noble <hi>Luther</hi> let the word of God come, and tho we had a hundred necks let them all ſtoop to it: and O ſaid Cypr: <hi>loquere magiſter bone, libenter te audio, &amp; cum adverſariis mihi &amp; cum iraſceris.</hi> O do not wound Conſcience in the Leaſt; as knowing that ye Cannot pleaſe God in any thing; unleſs ye carefully endeavour to pleaſe him in all things Coloſs. 1. v. 10. Jam. 2. v. 10, 11. Act. 24. v. 16. and think it not enough to leave off the practiſe of ſome ſins, unleſs ye forſake all; and unleſs ye forſake and loath, and find in your ſelves that indignation and Revenge againſt, and carefullneſs to avoid it 3 Cor. 7. v. 11.</p>
               <p n="8">8. Beware of doing any thing out of a doubting Conſcience, not being perſuaded of its lawfullneſs. Rom. 14. v. 14, 23. and O beware of going againſt
<pb n="41" facs="tcp:32567:22"/>thy light; if thou act againſt conſcience thou art not ſubject to Gods authority, but deſpiſeſt him ſpeaking (as thou ſuppoſeſt) by his deputy. Jam. 1 v. 5. <hi>But</hi> (ſaith Mr. Butroughs) take heed the Devil be not in the Conſcience, (as the place where he thinketh he may lodge, with leaſt ſuſpicion) that muſt be no ſanctuary to him, but he muſt be pulled from the horns of that Altar: and (ſaith he) if a man be proud and turbulent in his Carriage, 2. if he will not make uſe of means to inform his Conſcience, 3. if he Can give no rationall account for his actings, 4<hi rend="sup">ly</hi> if he go againſt his own principles, &amp;c. we fear the Devill is in that mans Conſcience.</p>
               <p n="8">8. Let ſelf deniall be thy dayly ſtudy, that being the firſt Leſſon of Chriſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>anity; &amp; if we be Chriſtians indeed it muſt be our dayly task, it being ſo neceſſary &amp; ſo hardly Learned: that Idol, miſtaken, miscalled, Satan ſerving, God diſhon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ouring, ſelf deſtroying <hi>SELF,</hi> keeping ſtill ſuch Court in the heart tho in part rene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wed, and having ſuch power and credit with us while in this ſtate, may readily be Intertained and inſinuat it ſelf where it is leaſt ſuſpected, in our profeſſions, reli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gious perfirmances, humiliations, ſufferings for, and labours in the Goſpel, yea and with our Zeale, unleſs we be very humble watchfull circumſpect; and that dead flie in the apotchecaries oyntment will make it ſtink; what we do for ſelf will not be reckoned as ſervice done to Chriſt. Matt. 16. v. 24. Gal. 6. v. 7, 8. hence.</p>
               <p n="9">9. Be much at home and at the work of, <hi>ſelf examination;</hi> be not ſtrangers where ye ought to converſe moſt, and with what ye ſhould be beſt acquainted: O Be diligent ſtudents in the book of your own hearts and Conſciences; ſearch after and diligently examine What have been, and are your works and way; and whatever Buſineſs you may ſlight or neglect forget not ſeriouſly to try and examine whether ye be in the faith or not; &amp; to Commune much with your own hearts, bringing your hopes and expectations, your profeſſion and perſuaſion, your works walk and way to the touchſton of the ſancturay, the word of God. Pſa. 4. v. 4. Pſal. 77. v. 6. 2 Cor. 13. v. 5.</p>
               <p n="10">10. Be Nathaniels Chriſtians Indeed, abhorring Hypocriſie as the bane of the Criſtian profeſſion: ſeek not a <hi>name,</hi> but to get the <hi>(new name)</hi> Rev. 2. v. 17. and to have the name of God engraven on thy holy Converſation. Rev. 3. v. 12. do not perform religious duties with ſound of trumpet Mat. 6. v. 5, 17, &amp;c. Say not, <hi>pulchrum eſt digito monſtrari, ac dicier hic eſt.</hi> Put not on more ſail then ye have ballaſt, and ſet not up a ſign at the door for what is not within: let not the wind of applauſe fill the ſails if your Courſe be heaven ward; the leſs dinne and noiſe ye make your profeſſion will be judged the more fincere; and ſince ſo many are ready to mock at Religion becauſe of the Hypocriſy of ſome empty profeſſors, with what care ſhould we abſtain from all appearance therof, that none have occaſion to laugh at us, for a piping voice, affected tone, a ſullen and auſtere countenance Artificiall ſighs and groans. Oh that in ſuch a day, ſo many ſhould deſire rather to <hi>appear,</hi> then <hi>be,</hi> and rather to <hi>ſhine,</hi> then <hi>have light.</hi> O let your ſincerity appeare as in your zeal for Gods worſhip and truth, ſo in your upright and righteous dealing with men, and in your civil courteous Kind carriage to
<pb n="42" facs="tcp:32567:23"/>wards them. <hi>I would</hi>
                  <note n="*" place="bottom">Farevvell Serm. p. <hi>157.</hi>
                  </note> 
                  <hi>(ſaith Mr. Watſon) try a morall man by the duties of the firſt table, and I would try a Profeſſor by the duties of the ſecond table.</hi> O ſtudy to anſwer your relation, and conſcientiouſly to diſcharge your Relative duties, theſe being the touchſton of our ſincerity: who will account him an ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſt Chriſtian, who is not a good husband, parent, Child, ſervant, neigh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bour, who is not upright in his dealing, faithfull in his promiſes, and ſincere in his Profeſſions? O let none have occaſion to ſay he met with a cheat, while he had to do with one who had a name in the Church! Joh. 1. v. 47. Rom. 2. v. 21, 28, 29. 1 Cor. 8. v. 5. hence.</p>
               <p n="11">11. Beware of a haughty heart and ſupercilious carriage, and doe not exerciſe thy ſelf in great matters, and in things too high for thee, above thy reach, and without thy Sphere Pſa. 131. v. 1, 2. ſtretch not your ſelf beyond your line, and leap not over the hedge leſt a ſerpent bite you; zeale is precious, it is a heavenly ſpark, but fire not kept within the chimney may conſume the houſe: when we medle with things without our reach, and play the Biſhops (as the word 1 Pet. 4. v. 15. importeth) in another mans Dioceſs, as we act without Gods warrant, ſo without his bleſſing, and may fear his hand: Ah from whence doth all miſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chief and confuſion Come, but from mens pride driving them beyond their line, and to act without their Sphere? and <hi>O what a quiet world ſhould we have</hi> (<note n="†" place="bottom">Chriſt. arm. part. <hi>2.</hi> Chap. <hi>2.</hi>
                  </note> 
                  <hi>ſaith Mr. Gurnal</hi>) <hi>if every thing and perſon knew, and kept its own place!</hi> and O if they (and how many ſuch are there) who are guilty herein would ponder what he further writeth concerning ſuch turbulent medlers <hi>what thou doeſt with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out a call, cannot (ſayeth he) be don in faith;</hi> 2. <hi>when thou thus acteſt thou puteſt thy ſelf out under Gods protection;</hi> 3. <hi>thou canſt have no comfort in ſuffering for what thou doeſt without thy Maſters call and warrant;</hi> 4. <hi>ſuch as dare go without their Sphere know not by what ſpirit they are led, it muſt be an erratique ſpirit that carrieth us out of our place;</hi> 5. <hi>men would conſider from what principle their irregular and eccentricall motions muſt flow,</hi> viz. 1 <hi>Pride,</hi> 2 <hi>diſcontent with their condition,</hi> 3. <hi>unbelief, (ſuppoſing that God did ſtand in need of their ſinfull and unruly motions to carry on his work)</hi> 4. <hi>blind and misinformed zeale.</hi> Ah if the eccentricall motions of the time were rightly analized, I fear it might be found that much of that which is fathe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red upon faith and truſting in God, and zeal for his glory, would be reſolved in unbelief, impatience, carnall policy, and ſelf ends.</p>
               <p n="12">12. Prize and eſteem perſons and things according to their relation to Chriſt; 1 Cor 2. v. 2. Coloſſ. 3. v. 11. 1. as to perſons love for Chriſt, and with <hi>B<g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>CER</hi> all in whom ye ſee any thing of Chriſt, tho they be not of your perſuaſion as to matters controverted among the faithfull, 1 Cor. 13 v. 2. and make conſcience of theſe duties towards the Bretheren, to which this love doth engage thee; v. 4.5. art thou perſecuted take heed thou doe not perſecute, and wound by thy tongue theſe who are perſecuted for Chriſt; Wo to them who add affliction to them who are afflicted for his name by their Cenſorious and uncharitable ſpee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ches, and by a tongue ſet on fire of hell, tho under a pretence of zeal for heaven. 2. as to things prize his word, and prize and own his truth while ſo many now are
<pb n="43" facs="tcp:32567:23"/>aſhamed of him and it; Buy his truth, but ſell it not ye know not its worth; Prov. 23. v. 23. if ye ſell, ye will looſe on the bargain, and repent of your folly; chuſe ſuffering rather then ſin, and to endure hard things rather then to part with this precious pearle: but tho ye ſhould prize every truth, and make Conſcience of every duty on which ye ſee Chriſts ſignet yet Lay out your zeal mainly for what is of moſt concernment; tho ye muſt not diſown or deny any truth, yet ye ſhould mainly <hi>contend for the faith once delivered to the ſaints.</hi> Jud. v. 3. and tho we muſt not abandon any duty, yet we muſt not with Hypocriticall Pha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſees prefer duties of leſs concernment: Matt. 23. v. 23. Be not like the Hypo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crites who will run many miles and upon many dangers in following pretended duties whereby they may get a name, and be noticed, and yet make litle Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcience of ſerving God in his own way if in it they be not noticed, and Cannot by it get a name. Once more prize Goſpel ordinances becauſe they bear his ſeale, keep up their Authority as being the meanes of ſalvation, the conduit of heavenly influences, and ſhining lights whereby blind mortals muſt be directed home<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward to their reſt. Rom. 10. v. 17. Rom. 1. v. 16. 1 Cor. 1. v. 21. and hence the many directions for keeping up the credit of ordinances in moſt deficult and dark caſes; Song. 1. v 8. Eph 4. v. 12, 13. Heb. 10. v. 25. Act. 2. v. 42. Act. 20 v. 7. Iude v. 10. do not Scare at your meat becauſe ye have a quarrel againſt the Cook who dreſſeth it; and ſlight not Chriſts ordinances becauſe of ſome failings in the adminiſtrators; do not think ye can honour God by deſpiſing his worſhip: Ah ſhall it become a mark of zeal, that hitherto hath been judged an evidence of profanity? the Lord knoweth how Sabbaths are ſpent by thoſe who ſtay at home while they are called to worſhip God in his publick ordinances: Conſider what a guiltineſs and provocation it is to withdraw from that part of his worſhip where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>by he is moſt honoured in the world! and what a hazard it is, and how much thou mayſt looſe by being abſent where God hath told us he would Come and bliſs us. Exod. 20. v. 24. <hi>Wheras</hi> (<hi>ſaith</hi>
                  <note n="*" place="bottom">Ruth. Lett. p. <hi>421.</hi>
                  </note> 
                  <hi>Mr. Rutherfurd</hi>) <hi>ye complain of a dead Miniſtery in your bounds; hunger of Chriſts making may thrive under Stewarts who mind not the feeding of his flock; the flock is obliged to ſeek him in the ſheepherds tents.</hi> [O Bliſſed ſoul that can look above a pulpit, and over a man up to Chriſt:] <hi>converſion and life is not tied to a mans lips and lively preaching,</hi> the bleſſing of ordinances muſt be look<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed for from their Author upon whom we muſt wait, <hi>we know (ſayes Reverend Beza with</hi> 17 <hi>Miniſters of Geneva in their Anſwer to non-conformiſts in England Ann.</hi> 1547.) <hi>that it is better to have half a loaf, then no bread</hi> if thou wert hungry indeed thou wouldſt ſay, better courſe fare, then to ſtarve.</p>
               <p n="13">13. Let your Moderation be known to all, your meekneſs, compaſſion, ten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derneſs, condeſcenſion: Philip. 4. v. 3. 1 Cor. 9. v. 19, 22. Rom. 15. v. 1. Now we are Come to a point wherein the ſafety, wellfare and beauty of the Church is ſo neerly concerned, viz. <hi>the unity of the faithfull among themſelves.</hi> Let us therfor ſtay a while in preſſing of it, and diſcovering the evil of Schiſm and Diviſion, how pernicious it is to the Church as diſpleaſing to God; and O if men perſecut, God ſmite, and we cut and rend, how lamentable muſt the caſe be;
<pb n="44" facs="tcp:32567:24"/>and how fooliſh we if we thus expoſe our ſelves to reproach, to be a gazing ſtock to Devils and men, provoke the Lord againſt us, and encourage perſecutors to proſecute their cruell deſigns? therfor let us here ſtay a while, and for our more clear and diſtinct procedur ſpeak to this head in ſeverall directions, wherof this ſhall be the firſt, O let your meek and Moderat converſation make you and your profeſſion amiable in the eyes of others: Be not furious and Jehu like drive with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out Conſideration, but ponder dangers and precipices that are in the way; we cannot exceed in our love to God, and zeal for his Glory, but it is eaſy and or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dinary to exceed in the ontgoings of our paſſion, which we are ready to father on our zeal; the famous <hi>Antony</hi> being askt by the fathers of that time, what was the vertue wherby a man was preſerved in the Offices of piety, that he may continue in the practiſe therof to the end? wiſely<note n="*" place="bottom">Cum haec queſtio eſſet propoſita inter Patres qua nam virtus Chriſtianum hominem in officiis pietatis recte conſervaret? &amp; alii aliter reſponderent, alii id commode jeſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niis vigiliisque, alii contemptu rerum externarum, alii per charitatis officia poſſe fieri cenſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bant; reſpondit tandem Beatus Antonius inquiens, omnia quae dixiſtis utilia ſunt Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtianis, ſed his principalis Gratia tribuenda non eſt, idque plurimorum fratrum caſus, confirmant qui verſantes in his obſervationibus deceptiſunt, eo quod in bono quod caepe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rant [modum &amp; diſcretionem] non tenuerunt: in omnibus ergo quae agimus diſcretio an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teponenda eſt: conſtat ſine diſcretionis gratia &amp; modo nullam perfici, vel ſtare virtutem poſſe.— Porro addidit Divus Antonius exemplum Heronis Senis, quo oſtendere pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tribus voluit non poſſe ſine gravi periculo corporis &amp; animae pretermitti modum ac diſcre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tionem] Vit. Antonii per Nozerenum ex Athanaſio pag. mihi <hi>109.</hi> The ſaying [<gap reason="foreign">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap>] nequid nimis] is well knowen tho litle obſerved.</note> anſwered, <hi>that Moderation and diſcre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion did herein excell; that tho the exerciſe of many Graces was neceſſary, yet the fall of raſh zelots might convince us that herein Moderation muſt have the preeminence.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="14">14. Be not ſelfwilled, turbulent, implacable, and tenacious in your own quarrell, and as to what your perſonall Intereſt may be Concerned in: <hi>take away</hi>
                  <note n="†" place="bottom">Ceſſet propria voluntas &amp; non erit infernum. Bern. Serm. <hi>3.</hi> de reſ.</note> 
                  <hi>(ſayes Bernard) mens will and there will be no fire in hell;</hi> and take away (may we ſay) paſſionat wilfull will and the fire of contention will die out, Prov. 13. v. 10. O But to be of a tractable humble condeſcending temper is a noble commenda<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion,<note n="‡" place="bottom">Apud Plutarch de cohibenda ira.</note> 
                  <hi>I will (ſayes Aſthines to Ariſtippus) alwayes acknowledge you the better and more worthy man, becauſe I began the ſtrife, and you the peace.</hi> hence.</p>
               <p n="15">15. Let the Athenian<note n="*" place="bottom">Conſult the Miniſters of the provinciall Synod at London [Iuſ. div. miniſt.] part. <hi>1.</hi> c. <hi>13.</hi> and Praeface with M. Burroughs his irenicum. pag. <hi>286.</hi>
                  </note> 
                  <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap> be eſtabliſhed, and a line of forgetful<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs drawn over all our differences, that they may be buried in oblivion: and let none ſay of thee, that when the faithfull are for peace thou art for war: O if thou have any zeal for the Glory of Chriſt, and the good of his Church walk by that Divine rule Phil. 3. v. 16. [Wherto we have already attained let us (ſaith the Apoſtle) walk by the ſame rule, minding the ſame things; and as for ſome par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticulars wherein we may differ, let us not preſs our own ſentiments on others
<pb n="45" facs="tcp:32567:24"/>but patiently wait till God revile his mind to us as to theſe.] [If (ſaith<note n="*" place="bottom">Gurn. Chriſt. arm. part. <hi>2.</hi> c. <hi>2.</hi> ſee alſo M. Burroughs Iren. c. <hi>10.</hi>
                  </note> 
                  <hi>M. Gurnal</hi>) the ſervants by their ſtrugling about the houſe dreſſing thruſt the child in the fire, and burn it, what thanks will they get from the parent the Maſter at his return: the Child (ſaith he) is religion, which is like to periſh by our debates and devi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſions] hence.</p>
               <p n="16">16. Let us mourn for our ſinfull, fooliſh, Church deſtroying, and ſelf de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtroying diviſions which have been both the meritorious and Inſtrumental cauſe of ſo much ruin; by theſe we have provoked God to wrath againſt us, reproacht the truth we profeſs, and made our ſelves a reproach, have played the Adverſaries Game, have encouraged and ſtrengthned their hands in their attempts againſt us, weakened our own hands, and have not pondered what our Lord Warned us of (tho ſo clear in it ſelf) Mark. 3. v. 24, 25. nor the ſaying (not more common then manifeſt) <hi>Divide &amp; impera.</hi> O then, <hi>Mark them that cauſe Diviſions, and by good words and fair ſpeeches deceive the hearts of the ſimple; Rom.</hi> 16. v. 17, 18. and, if there be any conſolation in Chriſt, if any comfort of love, if any fellow ſhip of the ſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit, if any bowells and Mercies let nothing be don through ſtrife or vain Glory, having the ſame Love and being of one accord: Philip. 2. v. 1, 2, 3. O how are we engaged to love theſe Miniſters, and eſteem them highly who are for peace unity moderation charity and love among the faithfull; Such Miniſters being a bleſſing to the Church while they live, and their Memory precious to poſterity; <hi>the or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nament of a meek humble and quiet ſpirit being in the ſight of God and man of a high price,</hi> and may be called the truly zealous ſincere Chriſtian his Crown, the character of a Goſpel like frame, the comfort of the Bretheren, and a noble attractive to allure and draw in thoſe who are without. 1 Pet. 3. v. 4. Coloſſ. 3. v. 12, 13, 14, 15. O then have no hand in renting and dividing the Church; is it not Chriſts body; Ah while the enemy is ſeeking to deſtroy it, wilt thou cut it in pieces? How much ſo ever of zeal may be pretended for ſuch a work, yet we are perſua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded from the word of truth, that <hi>only by pride cometh contention.</hi> Prov. 13. v. 10. the zealous M. Firmin ſpeaking of the wofull diviſions and many ſects then abounding in England, and the abominable blaſphemies vented by theſe who once ſeemed to have been moſt zealous and eminent profeſſors, <hi>think it not ſtran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ge (ſaith be) to ſee it ſo, for I knew the moſt famous, and who ſeemed the moſt zealous among them, and ſaw the bones of pride ſhamfully ſtick out in them all.</hi> Litle good can be expected from a prond zelot: O then while ye are aſſerting, ſtanding in defence of, and ſuffering for the faith, <hi>ſtudy to keep the unity of the ſpirit, the unity of the faith, the</hi>
                  <note n="†" place="bottom">
                     <hi>Eph.</hi> 4. v. 3.</note> 
                  <hi>unity of the Church in the bond of peace.</hi> If any would but reflect on Chriſts legacy and laſt words to his diſciples, his farewell Sermon, and ſolemn prayer Joh. 14 v. 27. Joh. 15, v. 12, 17. Joh. 17. v. 11, 21, 23. Or if any would ſeriously ponder the Apoſtles moſt pathetick exhortations, and the Arguments whereby he preſſeth theſe 1 Cor. 1. v. 10. Eph. 4. v. 33, &amp;c. Philip. 2. v. 1, &amp;c. Phil. 3. v. 15, 16. Rom. 12. v, 9, 10. 1 Theſſ. 4. v. 9. with many more to that purpoſe, and if any will call to mind the ſharp rebukes and checks given to, and
<pb n="46" facs="tcp:32567:25"/>the diſmall characters of ſeparatiſts and Church dividers, with the ſad regrate and Lamantations over them 1 Cor. 1. v. 11, &amp;c. 1. Cor. 3. v. 31. 1 Cor. 11. v. 18. Gal. 5. v. 20; Jud. v. 19. who (I ſay) conſidering theſe things could imagine that the tares of diviſion and diſcord among Bretheren could be ſown by any but the envious one, and his factors? Yet for the further conviction of Schismaticks, let us add ſomewhat more, begining with that Goſpel like prophecy of Chriſts King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom, that under it thoſe who are by nature wild like wolves Lions and boares ſhall ly down together, &amp; ſweetly feed: Iſa. 11. v. 6, &amp;c. &amp; did not Zacharias Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pheſy of Chriſt, <hi>that he ſhould guide our feet in the way of peace?</hi> Luc. 1. v. 79. 2 is it not a ſpecial promiſe in the Covenant of grace that the Lord will give us one heart, and one way? Jer. 32. v. 39. Ezek. 11. v. 19. and O what a ſtumbling block is it to the Jewes that they ſee not theſe propheſies and promiſes fullfilled in thoſe who are called Chriſtians? 3 is not Chriſt the prince of peace? Iſa. 9. v. 6. is not his goſpel the Goſpel of peace? Rom. 10. v. 15. is not peace included in our Chriſtian calling? 1 Cor. 7. v. 15. did not Chriſt die with peace in his lips? Joh. 14. v. 27. Joh. 17. v. 21. and after he aroſe from the dead, did he not ſalute his diſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ples with the bleſſing of peace? Ioh. 20. v. 19. and did not the Angles at his birth proclaim peace (as to, ſo) among the ſaints on earth? Luk. 2. v. 4. 4 has he not made love and concord the <hi>badge</hi> whereby his Genuine followers may be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>known, and appointed it to be worn as his Levery. Joh. 13. v. 35. and hath he not made it a <hi>gagge</hi> for ſtoping the mouth of adverſaries, who are ready blaſphe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mouſly to ſay <hi>he was not ſent of God?</hi> Joh. 17. v. 21, 23. 5 is not the Communion of ſaints an article of our creed and engraven upon, and ſealed by the Lords ſup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>per? which therfor beareth the name of <hi>COMM<g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>NION,</hi> as with Chriſt our head. 1 Cor. 10. v. 16. ſo among our ſelves; v. 17. 6 how pithily doth the Apoſtle as at one breath hold forth ſo many and ſuch ſtrong bonds of peace, and for kee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ping the ſaints in unity, that it might be ſuppoſed the Divell, the world, the pride of mans heart could not be able to burſt theſe aſunder? Eph. 4. v. 4, 5, 6. O precious and noble unity and Love? which makes us Look, like Chriſts diſciples and Chriſtians indeed; which is ſo beautifull and amiable in it ſelf, and ſo ſweet and comfortable to thoſe who follow it, which is ſuch a noble attractive and loadſton to draw in thoſe who are without, the ſtrength and ornament of the Church and a terrour to enemies; ſuch a noble guard againſt hereſies and errour, and as for preventing much miſchief from men, ſo many ſad judgments and ſtroaks from God: and what ſhall I ſay more? It is <hi>the bend of perfectneſs, above all things to be put on.</hi> Coloſſ. 3. v. 14. 1 Cor. 13. v. 13 O then wouldſt thou ſee God, 7amp; wouldſt thou have God to bliſs thee, <hi>follow peace and holyneſs.</hi> Heb. 12. v. 14. Rom. 12. v. 18. Pſa 133. v. 1, 3. Pſa. 34. v. 12, 14, and as the Lord from time to time hath viſibly bleſſed his people <hi>when they wal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ked together in unity and love,</hi> ſo when diviſions and contention once entred the Church, it proved a forerunner of judgements &amp; Gods wrath to break out againſt his people, &amp; of ſad perſecution from adverſaries: &amp; the judgements on, &amp; tragical ends of Schiſmaticks have been very ſignall and remarkable, as appeareth, if we begin at the firſt noted Schiſmaticks Korah and his company, and follow the Hi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtory
<pb n="47" facs="tcp:32567:25"/>from the firſt Chriſtian Churches to this day; eſpecially ſince the reforma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion happily begun by Zwinglius and Luther: we may not ſtay on a Hiſtoricall ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>count from Sleidens commentaries or Oſiander his Eccleſiaſtical Hiſtory, but for a brief view of Gods judgments on ſuch, we now only referre to D. Hoornbeck his ſum: contraverſ. P. 739. ſeqq. M. Baily his diſuaſive from the errours of the ti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>me, P. 13. ſeq<expan>
                     <am>
                        <g ref="char:abque"/>
                     </am>
                     <ex>que</ex>
                  </expan> and his vindication of that diſuaſive P. 5. ſeq<expan>
                     <am>
                        <g ref="char:abque"/>
                     </am>
                     <ex>que</ex>
                  </expan> And how zealous the truly zealous have been againſt Schiſm and diviſion, as being ſo pernicious to the Church, and diſhonourable to Chriſt, might at large be made appear from their writtings; But we may not ſtay on citations, elſe whom could we paſſe over who have written on that head? Yea thee brethren of the congregationall way (tho they went too great a length towards ſeparation yet) pretend to joyn with us in our teſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mony againſt ſeparation &amp; [Firmin Burronghs Norton] have written large treati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes againſt it, &amp; the five diſſentig Bretheren in their Apologeticall narration ſpeak to the ſame purpoſe: nay ſo odious is that imputation, that they who are moſt guilty are aſhamed to be branded therewith, and will be ready to cry out againſt it; ſo that Schismaticks bear that black mark of obſtinat Hereticks Tit. 3. v. 11. they are <hi>ſelf-condemned.</hi> But what judicious ſober Chriſtian will not joyn with that cloud of witneſſes, the Reverend<note n="*" place="bottom">Iuſ. Div. Miniſt. Epiſt. to the reader.</note> Miniſters of the provinciall Aſſembly at London in their commendation of zealous [Bucer] While he proteſteth, <hi>that he would gladly purchaſe with the loſe of his life the removing of the great ſcandall by the diviſion of Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtians,</hi> and with Luther (while in a good moode) profeſſing <hi>thrt he was as deſirous to embrace peace and eoncord, as he wat deſirous to have the Lord Jeſus propitious to him,</hi> and with them while they joyn with the Bretheren of the conregationall way in new England, proteſting <hi>they can truly ſay that it is far from them ſo to atteſt the diſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plin of Chriſt as to deteſt the diſciples of Chriſt; ſo to contend for the ſeamleſs coat of Chriſt, as to crucifie the Living Members of Chriſt; ſo to divide our ſelves about Church commu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nion, as through breaches to open a wide gape for a deludge of Anihichriſtian and Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fan malignity, to ſwallow up both Church and civil ſtate.</hi> Ah what tongue is able to expreſs the miſchiefe that hath come to the Church by firy contention and Divi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion? And who can produce ſo much as one Inſtance of any good that any where or any time came thereby. So that we may well conclud, that [in a true<note n="†" place="bottom">In vera &amp; reformata Eccleſia nullum malum eſt tantum, &amp; eccleſiae tam pernicio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſum ac malum Schiſmatis vid. Aquin. loc. citand.</note> re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formed Church there is no evil ſo great, and ſo Pernicious, as the evil of Schiſm,] which alienats the hearts of Bretheren, begetteth rancour and malice, and often new errours, and ſtrange opinions more dangerous then what at firſt was com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plained of, (for ſchismaticks being ſenſible how odious their ſchiſm is; muſt pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tend ſome great matter, and finding nothing that can be a juſt plea for their courſe, they muſt ſtart now queſtions not formerly moved, pick new quarrells, and if nothing can be found manifeſt truths muſt be called intolerable Errors; &amp; Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtacy and defection muſt be objected tho the matter in controverſy neither Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cern faith nor holineſs.) And thus obſtructeth remedies and hopes both of union and reformation: thence M. Norton thus pithily laments that evil, <hi>Alas, Alas
<pb n="48" facs="tcp:32567:26"/>(ſaith he) is there no</hi> medium <hi>bettween a BONIFACE and MORELLI<g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>S, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiveen papacy and Anarchy; if there be a</hi> myſtery <hi>of iniquitie in the one, is there not an</hi> univerſity <hi>of iniquity in the other?</hi> Ah how ſad is it to hear the magiſtrat as a faithfull nurſing father upbraid the Miniſters of Chriſt for betraying their truſt in deſtroy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing the Church with their indiſcreet debates, and ſchiſmatick practiſes? That while he laboured to increaſe and preſerve it they ſought to break it in pieces, and ruin it; thus the<note n="†" place="bottom">The two Philips Father and Son, having no time to do much ſervice to the Church, being ſo quickly cut off by [Decius] his conſpiracy, yet both are ſaid not only to have embra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ced the faith, but to have been martyrs for it: [uterque autem Decii opera interfectus eſt ob ſuſceptum baptiſmum, &amp; profesſionem Chriſtiani nominis.] Carion Chron. lib. <hi>3.</hi>
                  </note> firſt famous Chriſtian Emperour Great Conſtantine challenged ſeverall Biſhops in his time, while he writeth to theſe conveened in a Council at Tyre, <hi>how is it</hi>
                  <note n="(a)" place="bottom">Neſcio quid tot couventibus emolimini, niſi ut veritas ſubruatur: non advertitis quid domino placeat, ſed quomodo proximos opprimatis; Barbari per me Chriſtum colunt &amp; vos illius cultu neglecto contentionibus &amp; odiis deſeruitis, quae ad humanigeneris ten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dere videntur interitum Maſſaeus Chron. lib. <hi>10.</hi> pag. <hi>138.</hi>
                  </note> 
                  <hi>(ſaith he) that ye doe not inquire what is pleaſing to God, but ſtudy to oppreſs one another? And what is the fruit of your debates? The Barbarians by me have been brought to worſhip Chriſt, and ye mak his worſhip to be neglected by your Conten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions, which tend to the deſtruction of mankind;</hi> &amp; in another Epiſtle<note n="(b)" place="bottom">Veſtra diſcordia emergente Sacra Miſteria contemnuntur &amp;c. ibidem pag. <hi>135.</hi>
                  </note> he tells them [how great his griefe was becauſe of theſe, and obteſteth them to pity him, and to allow him ſome tranquillity of mind by ſeing them live as Brethren in unity; upbraiding them with the Carriage of Philoſophers (as we may now our Brethe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ren with Papiſts) among whom tho there be great diverſity of opinions, yet they conſpired together for the profeſſion, and their own ſafety in the unity of one bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy: But (ſaith he) by your diſcord the holy Myſteries are contemned, the Church deſpiſed, and the people rent aſunder in factions and parties] and with what in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dignation at the 1. generall Nicen council did he caſt their defamatory libells into the fire? As for primitive Chriſtians, they ſo abhorred ſchiſm that without ſcri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pture warrant (as Jerome ſuppoſeth) they ſet up a Biſhop (tho not a Lord prelat) above his Bretheren, to prevent and remedy it (which afterwards was judged to be an improper remedy, as often feeding, rather then Curing that malady) how<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ever thus their zeal againſt Schiſm was hereby manifeſted: But let us add ſome few other teſtimones, [he who departeth (ſaid)<note n="(c)" place="bottom">Eunod. apud Eprbeſ. inſtruct. Hiſt. lib. <hi>14.</hi> c. <hi>1.</hi>
                  </note> Eunodius from the unity of the Church offereth a fat ſacrifice to the Devil.] And ſaith<note n="(d)" place="bottom">Apud Gratian. cauſ. <hi>24.</hi> queſt <hi>1.</hi> c. alienus.</note> Cyprian, [he Cannot have God to be his father, who will not cleave to the Church as to his Mother,] <hi>and ſaith</hi>
                  <note n="(e)" place="bottom">Iren. adverſ. Haereſ. lib. <hi>4.</hi> c. <hi>62.</hi>
                  </note> 
                  <hi>Irenaeus,</hi> [Whatever good be pretended to Come by <hi>SCHISM,</hi> it can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not counterballance the evil of <hi>SCHISM,</hi>] which (ſaith<note n="(f)" place="bottom">Apud Gratian. cauſ. <hi>24.</hi> queſt. <hi>3.</hi> c. Inter.</note> Jerome) cannot long
<pb n="49" facs="tcp:32567:26"/>continue without Hereſy:] and<note n="(a)" place="bottom">Optat. de Schiſ. Donatiſt. lib. <hi>1.</hi>
                  </note> 
                  <hi>Optatus Milevitanus</hi> is not affraid to ſay that, <hi>Schiſm is the chief of evils:</hi> and judicious<note n="(b)" place="bottom">Ameſ. de Conſcient. caſ. lib. <hi>5.</hi> c. <hi>12.</hi>
                  </note> D. Ames durſt call it. <hi>Peccatum Graviſſimum;</hi> a moſt grievous ſin: but <hi>Optatus</hi> goes on telling us, [that it is a greater ſin then Homicid or Idolatry:] and<note n="(c)" place="bottom">Auguſt. de Baptiſ. contra donat. lib. <hi>1.</hi> c. <hi>8.</hi>
                  </note> Auſtin comes not ſhort of him, while he ſaith (having his eye as I ſuppoſe on what our Lord ſaith to Scribes and Phariſees Mat. 23. v. 15.) [if any be converted by Schismaticks from Idolatry, and infidelity, they are not gained, but deſperatly hurt by the wound of Schiſm] and <hi>Denis</hi> of Alexandria in his Epiſtle to the famous Church divider <hi>NOVAT<g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>S</hi>
                  <note n="(d)" place="bottom">Apud Euſeb. hiſt. Eccl. lib. <hi>5.</hi> cap. ult.</note> ſpeaketh to the ſame purpoſe, [thou ſhouldſt (ſaith he) rather have ſuffered any thing, then ſuffered the Church to be divided: it is a glorious nay I count it a more glorious Martyrdom that the Church may not be divi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded, then to be kept from ſacrificing to an Idol] not as if theſe judicious fathers would compare Schiſm with Idolatry and infidelity as to the immediat object, or ultimat end; as if the glory of God were as <hi>directly</hi> and <hi>immediatly</hi> concerned in Schiſm, as in Idolatry; but they conſidered the conſequents, and good of the Church; &amp; becauſe (as <hi>Denis</hi> tells us) a multitude is concerned in the michief from Schiſm, they lookt upon it as ſo pernicious an evil: and thus<note n="(e)" place="bottom">2. 2 <hi>Queſt.</hi> 39. <hi>Art.</hi> 2.</note> Aquinas doubted not to affirm, [that no ſin againſt the ſecond table was ſo great as Schiſm; and that in ſome reſpect it was greater then the ſin of infidells:] and if we would<note n="(f)" place="bottom">Ibid. quaeſt. <hi>37.</hi> art. <hi>2.</hi> &amp; quaeſt. <hi>37.</hi> art. <hi>2.</hi>
                  </note> conſult that Author we will find its geneologie and parentage, as alſo its daughters and ofſpring to be very diſhonourable.</p>
               <p>As for the properties of Schismaticks and ſeparatiſts, the Apoſtle tells us that 1. they are carnall and walk as men not as ſaints; 1 Cor. 3. v. 3. 2. that they are deceitfull, creeping in to houſes, and by good words and fair ſpeeches ſeek to deceive the hearts of the ſimple; 2 Tim. 3. v 6. 3 that they have a form of godli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs, but deny the power of it; and are ſuch as ſhould be avoided, and marked; ibid. v. 5. and Rom. 26 v. 17, 18. 4. that whatever they pretend, yet they are ſen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſuall not having the ſpirit; and cannot in that miſchievous work ſerve the Lord Jeſus; <hi>tho</hi> (<hi>ſaith</hi>
                  <note n="(g)" place="bottom">Par. in Rom. <hi>16. v. 17.</hi>
                  </note> 
                  <hi>D. Pareus</hi>) <hi>diviſions may be in the Church, yet they are the Divels work.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>We may not ſtay to diſcover thoſe diviſive principles ye muſt diſclaim; theſe diviſive paſſions and affections ye muſt abandon; and thoſe diviſive practiſes ye ought to guard againſt, and beware of: but for a diſcovery of theſe; with their proper remedies, let me remit you to M. Burroughs his golden <hi>IRENIC<g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>M:</hi> but O if Schiſmaticks would but conſider, that the Lord accounteth the injury don to his Church as offered to himſelf, that they who touch it touch the apple of his ey: now if the touch be ſo ſmarting as thus to cut rend and divide, how muſt he be concerned? [we have not (ſaith the Apoſtle, Heb. 4. v. 15.) an high prieſt that cannot be touched with the feeling of our ſores and infirmities:] how neerly then muſt he be touched with ſuch a wound as thus teareth and divideth his body?
<pb n="50" facs="tcp:32567:27"/>is not the Church his body? Eph. 1. v. 23. and are not we Members thereof, and of his fleſh and bones? Eph. 5. v. 30. will he not then reckon Schiſmaticks amongſt the piercers of his body, and eſteem the violence thus offered to the Church as if to himſelf? and Ah muſt he not have the heart of a tiger, who in a day of ſuch diſtreſs dare thus wound the afflicted? and can he call himſelf a friend, who while ene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mies are ſeeking to deſtroy it, dare divide rent and cut it in pieces? [Schiſm being (as<note n="*" place="bottom">
                     <hi>Par. in</hi> 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 11. v. 18.</note> 
                  <hi>D. Pareus</hi> ſpeaketh) as great a deſtruction to the Church, as the cutting of the hands or feet, or the dividing of the head in two is to the body.] Now let us ſhut up this direction with the words of great Auſtin, [to whom<note n="†" place="bottom">Aug. de Baptiſ. contra donat. lib. <hi>2.</hi> c. <hi>5.</hi>
                  </note> (ſaith he) will God reveale his truth, but to thoſe who walk in the way of peace? O remember we are men, and to miſtake and erre is a tentation common to men; but to love our own judgment ſo as to break the unity of the Church in preſſing it, is devi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liſh preſumption: to erre in nothing is the Angels perfection; and wanting the perfection of Angels, let us not run upon the preſumption of Devils.] hence.</p>
               <p n="17">17. Let us not be eaſily provoked, nor think evil of our Bretheren becauſe they differ from us in ſome points far removed from the foundation, &amp; having no direct influence on holyneſs; and perhaps not ſo clearly revealed, which may be, (&amp; are among the more ſober and judicious) amicably debated according to the ana<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>logy of faith: for while <hi>we know but in part, and ſee but through a glaſs Darkly,</hi> it is not ſuppoſable but there will be different apprehenſions and judgments concern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing ſuch matters and queſtions; in order to which the exhortation hath place (and when will we be ſo wiſe and ſelfdenied as to hearken to it) <hi>haſt thou faith have to thy ſelf befor God.</hi> Rom. 14. v. 22. and is not the rule clear, Philip. 3. v. 15, 16. <hi>Wherto we have already attained let us walk by the ſame rule, and if in other things there be diverſity of ſentiments, let us forbear one another till God reveale his mind to us Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerning theſe.</hi> Ah there being a ſweet harmony and unity in the faith, will we not come, or continue under the bond of peace, and with all lowlineſs and meekneſs forbear one another in love? Eph. 4. v, 2, 3. Oh who reflecting on the ſeven divine cords and bonds of love and unity held forth in the 4, 5, 6. following ver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes could imagine that a ſaint indeed could caſt theſe of? hence.</p>
               <p n="18">18. Let me obteſt you not to miſtake, nor put a wrong gloſs on the Commands to ſeperat, Come out from among, to have no fellowſhip with, yea not to eat or drink with ſuch and ſuch ſinfull perſons. 2 Cor. 6. v. 15, 17. 1 Theſſ. 3. v. 14. 1 Gor. 5. v. 11, &amp;c. elſe you may caſt your ſelves into a Labyrinth of intolera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble miſcarriages, errours and inconveniences; and be tempted to caſt of theſe bonds the light of nature, morality, and reaſon have laid on; and may with Hy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pocriticall phariſees Matt. 15. v. 5, 6. Pretend religion and Conſcience for caſting of the duties the law of God obligeth thee to perform to thy relations; wives may abandon their husbands, Children their parents, ſervants their Maſters, ſubjects their lawfull magiſtrates, and the flock their faithfull paſtors, contrary to the light of nature, to the <hi>fundamentall</hi> laws of Government Society and order, and the divine commands Coloſſ. 3. v. 11, 19, 20, 21, 22. Cor. 7. v. 10, 13, 14. 1 Pet. 2. v. 17, 18, 19. Heb. 13. v. 7, 17, &amp;c. But for underſtanding thoſe places
<pb n="51" facs="tcp:32567:27"/>wherin we are prohibited to have fellowſhip with unbelievers, with the pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fane, &amp;c. Ye would remember that many ſuch prohibitions were occaſionall, temporary, particular and not to be extended to all perſons, times, and occaſions; ſuch were many prohibitions to the Jewiſh Church, eſpecially in reference to the ſeven nations devoted to deſtruction; and in the new Teſtament, in reference to ſcandall, becauſe of the weakneſs of ſome new Converts; or 2. becauſe of ten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derneſs towards the converted Jews, notwithſtanding their adhering too tenaci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ouſly to ſome ceremoniall cuſtoms (which being once of Divine inſtitution were to be buried honorably) of which number that of ſeparation and keeping at a di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtance from ſuch and ſuch perſons, was not the leaſt, 3. becauſe of the great hazard to the infant Chriſtian Church from promiſcuous mixtures; eſpecially where Churches were not well conſtitute, and had no Elderſhip and conſiſtory erected: but 2 the prohibitions in the places cited do (as Calvin obſerveth) relate to Ido<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>laters, and do condemn all joyning with ſuch in their idolatrous worſhip; and 2. with theſe who were within the Church, after that by the ſentence of excom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>munication they were caſt out, and contumaciously perſevered in their wicked<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs; But if privat perſons were left to be judges in this matter, who ſeeth not what confuſion uncharitableneſs, and wrong judging might follow therupon? But 3. as to others, who are tolerat in the Church, and on whom no mark is ſet by the Elderſhip, yet continuing in their wickedneſs, and their carriage being ſcandal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lous we are forbidden to have any Intimat, voluntary, delightfull fellowſhip with ſuch; we ſtanding under no ſuch relation to them as obligeth us to a familiar fel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowſhip: and 4. when duty obligeth us to converſe with ſuch, we muſt take heed that we do not participat with them in their wickedneſs, or Incourage them in their ſinfull courſe: <hi>Cavendum eſt ne quo ſordium contactu nos inquinemus,</hi> ſaith<note n="*" place="bottom">Calvin. in <hi>2</hi> Cor. <hi>6.17.</hi>
                  </note> Cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vin, to whoſe accurate and judicious commentaries on the places on which men of ſectarian principles faſten their wild gloſſes,<note n="†" place="bottom">Paulus de jugo impietatis loquitur <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>. e. departicipatione operum quibus communi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>care chriſtianis fas non eſt: — Jugum ducere cum infidelibus nihil aliud eſt, quam operibus infructuoſis tenebrarum communicare, &amp; manum illis in ſignificationem conſen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſus porrigere. in <hi>v. 14.</hi> vid. etiam in <hi>1 Cor. 5, 11.</hi> &amp; in <hi>2 Theſ. 3, 14.</hi>
                  </note> we remit ſuch as would not be deluded by Separiſts: let us then ſearch the ſcriptures and compare theſe diligently. and we will find 1. that there is nothing in theſe prohibitions to ſcarre the moſt tender and circumſpect Chriſtian from fellowſhip, and familiar converſing with ſincere ſeekers of God, who keep the unity of the faith, notwithſtanding ſome dif<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ferences concerning matters of leſs importance, &amp; not ſo clearly revealed: 2 ſuch will find that there is nothing in theſe to hinder them from joyning in the ordinan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces of Chriſt with theſe from whom they thus differ; if the ordinances be pure, &amp; no ſinfull conditions of communion be impoſed on them: hence 3. ſuch will find in theſe no warrant to withdraw from ordinances becauſe of ſome failings in the adnimiſtrators, or the perſonall ſins of them who are to joyn and pertake of theſe ordinances; for their ſins cannot defile thee, nor polut the ordinances of Chriſt hence.</p>
               <p n="19">
                  <pb n="52" facs="tcp:32567:28"/>19. Walk by rule, and make no ſingular example or priviledge thy copy; let thy obedience be regular, and conform to ſtanding rüles rightly underſtord, and applied, ſo that that thou mayeſt be able to anſwer the queſtion Iſa. 1. v. 12. who required what thou doeſt, and who required it at your hand? Obedience if not regular deſerveth not the name, and a performance without a warrant is no duty; to ſupererogat is but to preſume, prevaricat provoke: there be in the word ſome ſpeciall, occaſionall, and temporary commands given to ſome, at ſome parti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cular time, and on a peculiar account, as theſe Matt. 10. v. 9, 10, 14, 19. Luk. 10. v. 14. 2 King. 4. v. 29, &amp;c. And there are ſome ſingular examples, as that of <hi>Phineas, Ehud, Iael,</hi> &amp;c. And if thou ſet up theſe for a rule thou mayeſt turn Quaker, Enthuſiaſt, Morellian, Libertin.</p>
               <p n="20">20. Give no offence, be tender in the matter of ſcandall either on the right or left hand, either by a wicked practiſe, or fond fancy and imagination, or by thy apoſtaſy and forſaking the way of truth and duty: however many pretending tenderneſs are not afraid to ſcandalize the faithfull. yet wo to that man by whom offence Cometh. Mat. 8. v. 7. 1 Cor. 10. v. 32, 33. 2 Cor. 6. v. 3. Phil. 1. v. 10. But tho ſome (whoever they be) may give, yet do not thou take offence: Ah ſhouldſt thou brake thy neck becauſe others have caſt a ſtumbling block in the way?</p>
               <p n="21">21. Love not to walk in untroaden paths, or to go alone; beware of ſingu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>larity as ſavoring of pride and Hypocriſy: tho thou muſt not be conformed to the world, and walk in the broad way for company-ſake. Rom. 12 v. 2. ſo that tho thou wert (as Elias once ſuppoſed he was) left alone, thou muſt not ſtep aſide to meet with others, and follow them in any ſinfull way, yet no plea from hence for an humorous factious conceited ſingularity: if ſayes Mr. Burroughs thy ſin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gularity appear, 1. in things that are taken notice of by others, and by which thou expecteſt to raiſe thy name; and if diſappointed in that, and others take litle notice of theſe things, or of thee for appearing for them, thou becomeſt in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>different; 2. if thou care litle for ſuch things when they come to be common; 3. if there be no evenneſs in thy way, and no proportion kept in thy courſe, but thou art ſingular in ſome odde notion or wild conceit and in things materiall darſt com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plie with, and conform (I doe not ſay to the law, or with the ſaints but) to the world, thy ſingularity is humorous and conceited.</p>
               <p n="22">22. Watch over thy tongue and bridle it; and abominat backbitting, defa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ming, and wounding of ons name and reputation and ſpeaking evil of the abſent, as being the fruit and evidence of a tongue <hi>ſet on fire of hell;</hi> Tit. 3. v. 2. Jam. 1. v. 26. and 3. v. 6. Pſal. 15. v. 3. Levit. 19. v. 16. Prov. 11. v. 13. 2 Cor. 12. v. 20, &amp;c. Tho we may ſpeak of the faults of others 1. by way of regrate, 2. for caution, 3. for uſefull information, and 4. to offer a materiall for prayer either for them. or for preventing the evil feared by them; Yet how abominable and unchriſtian like is it, to ſpeak of the faults of others 1. with delight, 2. frequent<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly ordinarly and at every turn. 3. upon ſlender litle or no ground, 4. if of the faithfull, miſconſtruing their laudable actions, or venting groſs calumnies, and ſpreading lying reports of them; which ſin is yet more aggravat if of thoſe who
<pb n="53" facs="tcp:32567:28"/>are ſuffering for righteousneſs ſake, and if thus affliction be added to the afflicted, and tongue perſecution of the ſadly perſecuted for Chriſt: ſhall we count ſuch zealous and religious? nay ſaith the Apoſtle pretend what they will <hi>their Religion is vain.</hi> Jam. 1. v. 26. And as this ſin is ſo odious to God, and<note n="*" place="bottom">Veteres legiſlatores non ignoraverunt male dictis quam malefactis gravius abſentes laedi, difficiliuſque a pleriſque contumeliam perferri quam damnum Camer hor. Suc. c. <hi>3.</hi>
                  </note> injurious to our Bretheren whom we ſhould love as our ſelves, ſo it is abominated by very pagans ſo that one of their<note n="†" place="bottom">Abſentem qui rodit amicum, qui non defendit alio culpante — hic niger eſt, hunc tu Romane caveto. Horat. lib. <hi>1</hi> Serm. <hi>4</hi> Sat.</note> poets accounted it unbeſeeming a Roman to company and converſe with ſuch: Ah how far now a dayes are many who would be accounted good from <hi>BERNARD</hi> his good mans temper? Who when he heard of the fall of any wept, and (as reflecting on Galat. 6. v. 1.) in compaſſion to him, and out of ſenſe of his own frailty ſaid <hi>ille hodie ego cras,</hi> if he to day hath, I to morrow may fall: O if that diſtichon which the eminent <hi>A<g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>STIN</hi> cauſed writ over his table, were engraven on our doores, (and in it for his <hi>Menſam</hi> were put our <hi>aedem.</hi>)</p>
               <q>
                  <l>Quisquis, amat dictis abſentem rodere amicum,</l>
                  <l>Hanc menſam vetitam noverit eſſe ſibi.</l>
               </q>
               <p n="23">23. O let not a lying tongue be found in you, a thing ſo odious in it ſelf, ſo unbe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeeming a man, much more a Chriſtian: Ah art thou a ſufferer for the truth, <hi>and ſhal a ly be found in thy right hand?</hi> Wilt thou not hearken to the exhortation Eph. 4. v. 25? But if thou wilt not, then look on that ſad word Rev. 12. v. 27. and 22. v. 15. And ſee thy name written among the dogs that muſt abide without, and cannot enter into the new Jeruſalem.</p>
               <p n="24">24. Let God have your firſt and laſt thoughts every day; 1. in the morning asking your ſouls what ye may do for your Maſter his honour and Intereſt that day, conſidering what opportunities of ſervice may be offered in it, and ſet out with a Reſolution to walk with him, and to ſet him befor you in all ye go about, guarding againſt the ſnares and temptations ye may be triſted with in your trade buſineſs company: O watch and pray that ye enter not into temptation, Mat. 26. v. 41. Mat. 6. v. 13. and 2. at night allow no ſleep to your eyes till ye call your ſelves to an accomt how that day hath been imployed, what ye have don in it for God, (what ſervant dare ſpend a whole day not minding his Maſters work) and whither ye have ſaid or don any thing againſt his holy commands, and to provoke him to wrath; and think it a loſt day in which thou haſt made no advance heaven<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward, and a ſad day were in thou haſt gon out of the way, and ſtept aſide; if the dark night of Death ſurprize thee while thou art out of the way, where wilt thou lodge to all Eternity? O judge your ſelves dayly, that ye be not judged of God; 1 Cor. 11. v. 31. have your accompts made, your ſummons may be to a ſhort day: O let not thy night thoughts and frame provide fewel for carnall laſcivious or Satanicall dreams, tempt not Satan to ride on thy fancy while thou art a aſleep and knoweſt not how it is ſet a work, and where away it runneth; eſpecially ſince
<pb n="54" facs="tcp:32567:29"/>thou knoweſt not but that thou mayeſt awake in Eternity: Oh what other perſons are we while ſleeping, then when awake? is not ſleep a<note n="*" place="bottom">Stulte quid eſt ſomnus gelidae niſi mortis imago, ſaith the Poet, but yet the difference is great, for when Death hath once opened our eyes either in heaven (as he Pſal. <hi>17. v. 15.</hi> was confident his would be) or in hell (as his Luk <hi>16. v. 23.</hi>) We ſhall ſleep no more to all eternity, as having no more a mortall body calling for eaſe by ſleep, and ſetting the cauſes a work that bring it on.</note> ſhadow of death, and the fancy then let looſe of the conduct of reaſon and Religion? How much then are we Concerned to commit its conduct to him who neither ſlumbreth nor ſleepeth?</p>
               <p n="25">25. Take keed and watch thy heart with all diligence, that it cleave not to the world (or any idol in it, any ſenſuall and periſhing object or luſt-feeding occaſion) with an Adulterious embracement, for if thou thus ſet up an Idol, it will ſteale away thy heart from God, provoke him to wrath againſt thee, and may bring on ſpirituall and temporall judgments: Let not thy father complain of thy unkind<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs, ſeek his face dayly, continuing inſtant in prayer, let not Satan rob thee of that time ſet apart for privat prayer, or with thy family; &amp; if thou wouldſt not unfit thy ſelf for a fellowſhip with him, keep thy heart looſe of the Creature, &amp; in the intervalls of ſet or occaſionall prayer, let ſome thought of God, or ſome deſire darted up to him be imployed for guarding againſt that earthly mindedneſs and indiſpoſition that unfitteth thee for a communion with God: who knows (but he who obſerveth his heart, and what is its frame, and he who hath experi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>enced) what are the ſoul-enriching advantages of ſuch ſhort <hi>ejaculations</hi> and Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrophes to God? by theſe ſwift meſſengers we may keep a conſtant correſpon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dence with heaven, and carry on a ſpirituall trade there, and no trade calling or buſineſs needs obſtruct this ſpirituall traffique and commerce, ſuch ſhort <hi>paren<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>theſes</hi> will make no Conſiderable Interruption in our wordly buſineſs and employ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment; but if thou ſuffer thy heart to ſtay too long here below, it is ready ſo to faſten on the Creature, and take ſuch deep root in the earth, that it will not be eaſy for thee to pull it off, or to lift it up when thou doeſt look to God; but by ſuch ſpirituall diverſions it may be kept in ſome ſpiritual frame, that when the Lord either by his providence, or by the inward breathing of his Spirit ſaith to us, (as to him Pſal. 27, v. 8.) ſeek ye my face, our hearts with him may reply <hi>thy face Lord will we ſeek.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="26">26 Prepare for ſuffering, and dayly take up thy croſs; take a lift of it befor it be laid on that thou mayeſt be the fitter to bear it when it comes, and thou canſt not flee from it but by the back door of ſin, that looketh hell wards: do not thou that has not yet reſiſted unto blood, ſay the worſt is paſt, and thus feed thy fancy with hopes of better dayes; but tho thy mountain ſtood as ſtrong as Jobs once ſeemed to do, if with him thou would carry ſutably under it, with him Job 3. v. 25. forecaſt; and with a fear of vigilancy (but not of diſtruſt and dejection) provide againſt it, <hi>A warned man (we ſay) is half armed:</hi> ask thy ſoul then what thou wouldſt ſuffer for Chriſt, and if thou darſt<note n="‡" place="bottom">
                     <hi>Rom,</hi> 8. v. 35.</note> ſay <hi>ſhall tribulation, or diſtreſs, or perſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cution, or famine, or nakedneſs, or peril, or ſword ſeperate me from the Love of Chriſt, or make me deny him, and his truth? God forbid.</hi> [there are (ſaid a worthy Divine)
<pb n="55" facs="tcp:32567:29"/>none in heaven but <hi>Martyrs,</hi> and doth not our Bleſſed Lord ſay the ſame? Mat. 16. v. 24, 25. Mat. 10. v. 33, 37, 39. Mark. 8. v. 38, &amp;c. If thou be not ready to part with life and all at Chriſts call, thou cannot be his diſciple: But thou mayſt thus offer up thy ſelf to Chriſt, as Abraham did his Iſaac, tho he hold the hand of perſecutors, as he did the hand of Abraham, and ſuffer thee to eſcape; and if there be a ready mind, ye need not be diſcouraged through the ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prehenſion of the greatneſs of the tryall, the cruelty of perſecuters, &amp;c. Or of thy own weak<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs; he will proportionat the burden to thy back, and if he lay more on, he will give more ſtrength; and hath he not told thee what to do when thou findeſt it heavy? And bidden thee caſt both it and thy care upon himſelf, promiſing that he shal ſuſtain thee. Pſal. 55. v. 22. 1 Pet. 5. v. 7. and that he will not ſuffer that to be tempted above that thou art able, but will with, &amp;c. 1 Cor. 10. v. 13. O ſaid one, I cannot burn for Chriſt, but shortly after he was burnt in his shop by an accidentall fire; what canſt thou not burn for Chriſt, but muſt for a luſt? canſt thou not for a short while endure burning on earth, but wilt rather dwell with everla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſting burnings, and be a prey to theſe for ever.</p>
               <p n="27">27. Put a good conſtruction on providence as knowing and firmly believing <hi>that all the paths of the Lord are mercy and truth to ſuch as keep his Covenant,</hi> Pſal. 25. v. 10. that he is a father when he ſmites, as wel as when he ſmiles, and that tho provoked by the miſcarrriages of his Children, yet ſmiteth in love, and thus dealeth with them as ſons; and never taketh the rod in his hand but if need be, and alwayes for their good Heb. 12. v. 7, 8. 1 Pet. 1. v. 6. hence.</p>
               <p n="28">28. Let us hope, and patiently wait for the ſalvation of God; do not ſay the dayes are evil, and we will neever ſee it better; let us look over our deſervings, and up to the bowells of our kind father who <hi>tho he cauſe grief yet will have compaſſion, according to the multitude of his Mercies. Lam.</hi> 3. <hi>v.</hi> 31, 32. <hi>hence it is good that a man should hope, &amp;c.</hi> v. 26. the falſe Prophets of old pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pheſied of peace and proſperity, and thou mayeſt prove a falſe Prophet in fortelling evil and adverſity; the Lord hath a way of ſoveraignity, unſearchable to us, and in which he often walked towards his people in their deliverances from the ſadeſt adverſity; look on Iſrael in Egypt, in Babylon, &amp;c. And conſider what their frame was, whither it called for ſuch a Mercy and deliverance, as they were triſted with, many ſleep in the furnace, (and O what an evidence of ſtupidity muſt that be) untill the Lord open their eyes by an aſtoniſhing deliverance. Ezek. 16 v. 61, 62, 43. O then do not limit the Lord either as to a work of mercy or judgment; hence 1 be not ſecure but provide for a ſtorm, a more boiſterous ſtorm and hoter ſurnace; yet 2. caſt not away your conſidence, but live by faith waiting upon him who hideth his face untill he appear for the comfort of his people, ſtanding upon thy watch tower to ſee what he will ſay, as know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing the viſion is for an appointed time, and that at the end it will ſpeak and not ly; and therfor tho it tarry we should wait for it, becauſe it will ſurely come, yea tho to our apprehenſion it may, yet beyond the fit and beſt time it will not tarry: Habb. 2. v. 13. Heb. 10. v. 37. Pſa. 102 v. 13: it ill becometh his Children to be jealous of ſuch a father, it cannot but be acceptable to him as to look up to him, ſo to wait for, and expect good from him 1. if we make not haſt, 2. if with ſubmiſſion, 3. if in humility, and 4. if in a way of obedience and hearkning to his voice: and what evil (I pray) can there be in it, if we look to ſee him appear for our comfort? a Job could ſay tho he ſlay I will truſt; Job: 13. v. 15. can the caſe be more ſad, the provoca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion greater, and the diſtreſs more remedileſs then it lookt to be then while the Lord by his Prophets called his people to hope and wait for his ſalvation? Lam. 3. v. 24, 25, 26. Mic. 7. v. 78. Hab. 2. v. 1, &amp;c.</p>
               <p n="29">29. Let me Intreat that under theſe humbling diſpenſations ye would carry humbly: and o let your deportment ſute your Condition as to your garments; Is not the Lord to day ſaying to us what once he ſaid to that people Exod. 33. v. 5. <hi>put off thy ornaments &amp;c.</hi> Ah what a pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vocation muſt it be in a day of the Lords wrath, and of zions ſad diſtreſſe to indulge and ſatis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fie a vain airy humour in conforming your ſelves to the frothy empty prodigalls of the time, whoſe work is to adorn the body ſcarce minding they have a ſoul? What a ſad ſight then muſt it be to behold the exiles for Chriſt walking in <hi>Satans Livery,</hi> and to ſee their prodigality, levity, vanity engraven on their apparell? And O how Great is the guiltineſs of the preachers of the
<pb n="56" facs="tcp:32567:30"/>Goſpel if they have not <hi>learned of their Maſter</hi> (<hi>Mat.</hi> 11. <hi>v.</hi> 29) <hi>to be meek and lowly in heart;</hi> and if they be not parterns of humility and Gravity, as in their apparell, ſo in their whole de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>portment, abhoring a high look, ſaucy carriage, and every thing that might look like an in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dication of pride, and of high and overvaluing thoughts of them ſelves, as they would have their Miniſtery ſuccesfull; ſeriously conſidering that <hi>PRIDE</hi> covetousneſs profanity in the preacher do moſt effectually preach up Atheiſme and Infidelity in the hearers; eſpecially let novices and young preachers take heed <hi>they be not lifted up with pride, and fall into the condemn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of the Devil:</hi> 1 <hi>Tim.</hi> 3. <hi>v.</hi> 6. Oh what a ſad prognoſtick of wrath is it, that this genera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion (yea lately and ſo quickly) in vanity and prodigality (eſpecially as to apparell attendants table and adorning of honſes) have arrived at ſuch a hight beyond their Anceſtors? Tho folly be at the <hi>Bottome</hi> of every ſin, yet not ſo written in the <hi>face</hi> of other ſins as in this; for in ſtead of that reſpect and Credit men ſeek to reap by their pride, they meet with envy: reproach, disdain.</p>
               <p>Time would fail me if I did here inſiſt, therfor in a word ſummarily. O Be intreated in the Lords name <hi>to exerciſe your ſelves to have alwayes a Conſcience void of offence toward God and to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward man, Act.</hi> 24 <hi>v</hi> 16. <hi>rendering to all their dues, doing wrong to none, and owing no Man any thing but to love one another; and whatſoever ye would that men should do to you, do even ſo to them: <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>is the law of God and the law of nature requireth of you, this the prophets taught, and all faithfull <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="4 letters">
                        <desc>••••</desc>
                     </gap>iſters exhort unto, whither ye will hear or forbear:</hi> Mat. 7. v. 12. O do not then ſay, what muſt I do? And what doth the Lord require of me? Do but reflect on this Comprehenſive clear and plain directory, and thou mayeſt there read and diſcern thy duty towards Man: and love<note n="*" place="bottom">Delectio ſola diſcernit inter filios Dei &amp; filios Diaboli — Baptizentur omnes, Intrent Eccle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſias, &amp;c. non diſcernuntur filii Dei a filiis Diaboli niſi Charitate: magnum judicium, magna diſcretio, quicquid vis habe, hoc ſolum non habeas nihil tibi prodeſt; hoc habe, &amp; impleſti legem. Auguſt. trace. <hi>5.</hi> in <hi>1.</hi> Johan. ad. c. <hi>2.</hi> v. <hi>10.</hi>
                  </note> to our neighbours (which oblidgeth us to the Performance of all relative duties towards others) on which that directory is founded, is the fulfilling of the law Rom. 13. v 10. O then do not lay the blame on thy Ignorance (tho it may be Groſs, and thy guiltineſs upon that account very great) <hi>hath not the Lord shewed thee O man what is good? and what doth the Lord require of thee, but to do juſtly, and to love Mercy, and to walk humbly with thy God.</hi> Mic. 6. v. 8. thou ſtandeſt under many relations; haſt received many talents, and haſt many opportunities for ſervices and the day of accompts is Coming apace, and cannot be <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> off; O then for the Lords ſake; for thy ſouls ſake, for diſtreſſed zions ſake walk circumſpectly, and take heed to your ſteps, walk futably to thy profesſion and principles, ſutably to thy vows and engagements, ſutably to thy relation place and rank, and ſutably to the times to thine and the Churches tryalls and di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtreſſe: and be Intreated to lay to heart, to repent, and mourn for, 1. thy neglecting and too often omitting of duty, 2. thy remiſſneſs deadneſs and formality in worship, 3. Miſpent Sabbaths, 4. Careleſs and ſeldom reading the ſcriptures, 5. the neglect of family worship and duties, 6. the unfutablneſs of our Carriage and converſation to the holy Goſpel of Chriſt, 7. our unſenſiblineſs of the dishonour don to God, 8. wour living by ſenſe and not by faith, 9. our impatience murmuring and repining at croſs diſpenſations, our want of ſympathy with ſuffering believers and not communicating to their neceſſities: O mourn for, and be more ſenſible of theſe grievous provocations if thou wouldſt have the Lord to hide thee in this day of his wrath, and himſelf to be a ſanctuary and hiding place for thee; if thou wouldſt be among the number of theſe marked ones whom the Lord will ſpare when the devoring Angel goeth forth to ſmite, &amp; that however the times go thou mayeſt have thy ſoul for a prey. Now that the Lord would preſerve thee from all evil, and enable thee to keep the word of his pati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence, that thou mayeſt be kept from he hour of temptation that is Coming to try them that dwell on the Earth: (Rev. 3. v. 8.10.) and that in ſuch a ſad hour thou mayeſt be kept from falling and after that thou haſt (if need be) ſuffered a while may be preſented faultleſs befor the preſence of Chriſts Glory, is the prayer of.</p>
               <closer>
                  <signed>Your ſympathizing friend, companion in tribulation and patient waiting for the Kingdome of God, and your ſervant in the Goſpell of Jeſus Chriſt.</signed>
               </closer>
            </div>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
            <pb facs="tcp:32567:30"/>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
